<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ Evangelii, or, A vindication of the Gospel, with the establishment of the law being a reply to Mr. Steven Geree's treatise entituled, The doctrine of the Antinomians confuted : wherein he pretends to charge divers dangerous doctrines on Dr. Crisp's sermons, as anti-evangelical and antinomical / by Robert Lancaster ...</title>
            <author>Lancaster, Robert, b. 1603 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49230</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5714</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13212292</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13212292</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 425:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ Evangelii, or, A vindication of the Gospel, with the establishment of the law being a reply to Mr. Steven Geree's treatise entituled, The doctrine of the Antinomians confuted : wherein he pretends to charge divers dangerous doctrines on Dr. Crisp's sermons, as anti-evangelical and antinomical / by Robert Lancaster ...</title>
                  <author>Lancaster, Robert, b. 1603 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for a friend of the authors, and sold by Will. Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [7]-[8] at beginning and p. 64.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Geree, Stephen, 1594-1656? --  Doctrine of the Antinomians ... confuted.</term>
               <term>Antinomianism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Vindiciae Evangelii:</hi> OR, A VINDICATION OF THE GOSPEL,
WITH THE <hi rend="blackletterType">Eſtabliſhment</hi> of the
<hi rend="blackletterType">Law.</hi> BEING A Reply to Mr. <hi>Steven Geree</hi>'s
Treatiſe, ENTITULED, <hi>[The Doctrine of the Antinomians Confuted:]</hi>
WHEREIN He pretends to Charge divers Dangerous Doctrines on Dr.
<hi>Criſp</hi>'s SERMONS, as Anti-Evangelical and Antinomical.</p>
            <q> The Righteouſneſs of God without the Law is manifeſted,
being witneſſed by the Law and the Prophets, 
<bibl>Rom. 3.21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q> Do we make void the Law through Faith? God forbid; yea, we
eſtabliſh the Law, 
<bibl>v. 31.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q> Who ſhall lay any thing to the Charge of God's Elect? It is God
that justifieth, who is he that condemneth? It is Chriſt that dyed,
<hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <bibl>Rom. 8.33,34.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q> The Stone which is ſet at nought by the Builders, is become the
Head of the Corner, 
<bibl>Act. 4.11. Pſal. 118.22.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By ROBERT LANCASTER, Late Miniſter of the Goſpel, ſometime
at <hi>Quarly,</hi> and <hi>Amport</hi> in <hi>Hampſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for a Friend of the Authors, and Sold by
<hi rend="blackletterType">Will. Marſhall</hi> at the Bible in
<hi>Newgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98510:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98510:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT may be expected by thee, to have ſome ſhort account of the
late Reverend and Learned Author of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, concerning whom, they
that knew him well, can ſay, That his Worth was little known in the World;
his whole LIFE being ſpent in a Retiredneſs from it, for the moſt
part.</p>
            <p>It is the ſame <hi>Robert Lancaſter</hi> who Wrote the Preface
prefixt to Dr. <hi>Criſp's</hi> firſt Sermons; where may be ſeen, what
deſign he proſecuted in his after-Writings, in the Defence of the Doctrines
delivered by the ſaid Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> and where may be had a taſte of
his ſweet and gracious Spirit, wherein he was a Teaching Example to all that
were acquainted with his ordinary Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; He walked in a chearful,
ſerious practice of Holineſs, and though his pilgrimage here was attended
with a ſucceſſion of great outward Afflictions, yet he ſeemed to bear
them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Murmurring, and to live by Faith much above them.</p>
            <p>Not long before he finiſhed his Courſe here, it was, that he,
together with others, were Removed from the Publick Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his
Miniſtry, which was attended with many diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult Circumſtances, as to his
outward concerns. But yet the Bitter Oppoſition that had been, and continued
to be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome great truths of the Goſpel, by perſons of no
ſmall Figure, cauſed him to ſet himſelf to the Vindication of them, and
to ſhew the great Miſtakes of Mr. <hi>Rutherford,</hi> Mr.
<hi>Gataker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Geree,</hi> and their
Miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting great Truths, and in their Injurious charging of
perſons, <pb facs="tcp:98510:3"/> which he performed in a ſpirit of Meekneſs, wherein
he excell'd, and manifeſted it in publick, as well as private Diſputes upon
the ſame account, when called thereto; and with no leſs dexterity, being
thereto furniſhed, not only by a distinct Underſtanding of Divine
Mysteries, but a great. Accurateneſs in the knowledge of the Originals, and
of all the Oriental Verſions, being (it may be) one of the exacteſt
Gramarians in all thoſe Languages (as well as in the other) of his time.</p>
            <p>He Publiſhed little in his Life, being a man of a moſt
peaceable and humble Diſpoſition, of great backwardneſs to ſhew
himſelf; whether this his Inclination, or ſome other Reaſon, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him
from Publication of his Writings, it is not eaſie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine now, neither
is it of concern to us; but whatever was the Reaſon, delayed it was, and God
called him home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to reſt from his Labours; ſome of which the
Intelligent Reader may ſee, do here follow him; for ſo God would have it to
be, his Friends entruſted with his Manuſcripts (of which more may follow
this as a Firſt Part) being fully perſwaded, that they had a loud Call of
Providence, to bring out this Light that had ſo long been kept under a
buſhel, and hold it forth now as in a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time to the Church of
Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And leſt any ſhould be hindred from the benefit of it by a
preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate opinion, That the ſaid Author was an <hi>Antinomian</hi> and
<hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertine,</hi> an unbyaſt mind may be ſatisfied from his Preface to
Dr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> that he was neither, if he retain a right Underſtanding
of what thoſe Sects hold, and will but duly weigh what this Holy Man ſaith
there in the juſt Vindication of himſelf, and others, from that Charge:
Part of which only for brevity ſake, and for the information of ſuch as
have not read the ſaid Preface, or, have it not by them, we may rehearſe
here.</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:98510:3"/> 
               <p> As for us, we make not void the Law, but eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh it: We
Affirm, That it remaineth in its full force and power, not only of commanding,
but alſo of Exacting and Terrifying, of Curſing and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every Son
of <hi>Adam</hi> that is under it, without abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the leaſt jot or
tittle, and whether this be Antinomianiſm or no, let the Church of Chriſt
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, and Judge by the Word of Chriſt.</p> 
               <p> And as for the Imputation of Libertiniſm, if they mean that
which <hi>Calvin</hi> Chargeth the Libertines with, in his Book againſt them,
We utterly diſclaim it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Here it is moſt manifeſt, That he is not for the vacating of
the Law, neither as to Precept or Sanction, but holds ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly with the
Aſſembly in this Point, whereto Others that are ſo ready to make this
Charge, have ſufficiently declared their Contrariety.</p>
            <p>But yet it is not to be avoided, but notwithstanding this, or what
elſe can be ſpoken, ſome Men regarding not ſo much as common Ingenuity,
may charge the Doctrines here defended for Antinomianiſm, as the
Antagoniſts to them in his time did, and many at this day do; and no wonder,
if we are not without ſuch now, who brand the Preaching of the Goſpel to
diſtreſſed Conſciences. The pardoning of Sinners as Sinners. And divers
other Vital Doctrines of the Goſpel, for ſuch Hereſie; yea, ridicule and
ſcoff at the inviting of wretched miſerable Sinners unto <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt.</hi> Muſt we therefore loath and abhor theſe Glorious Fundamental
Truths, becauſe ſome men (pretending their Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in the Churches) do thus
reproach them? No, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, though this may be a ſtumbling-block laid
before the eyes of the Blind, yet <hi>Wiſdom ſhall be juſtified of her
Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:98510:4"/> and none ſhall always beguile them with enticing
Words, or affrighten them, by cloathing Truth in a Bear-skin. For ſuch as
have once truly tasted the Lord is gracious, will not be ſoon moved from him
who hath called them to Glory and Vertue, according as his Divine Power hath
given unto them all things that pertain to Life and Godlineſs through the
Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him: But as they have received Chriſt, ſo they will walk
rooted and built up in him, eſtabliſhed in the Faith, as they have been
taught, abounding therein with Thanksgiving.</p>
            <p>As for the enſuing ſhort Treatiſe, and what may follow, if
God pleaſe, they will undoubtedly recommend themſelves to the candid
acceptance of the Intelligent and Unprejudiced Reader, by their own Weight and
Evidence taken from the Word of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore need not a Prefatory
Recommendation, neither is it any way meet to impoſe upon the Reader, or
anticipate his Judgment by any Human Authority in Divine Myſteries. The
Benefit, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and Service of the Church, and the promoting the Truths of
Chriſt, were deſigned in this Holy Mans Undertaking at firſt, and it is
now in the Publiſhing of it, which great and deſirable Fruit, may it but be
reached and attained, Let the GOD of all Peace and Truth have the Glory of it,
and the Lord JESUS CHRIST, the Way, the Truth and the Life, be for ever
Magnifyed. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98510:4"/>
            <head>BOOKS Sold by <hi>Will. Marſhal</hi> at the Bible in
<hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THE Labours of <hi>John Bunyan,</hi> Author of the
<hi>Pilgrims Progreſs,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Paſtor of
the Congregation at <hi>Bedford,</hi> Collected, and Printed in <hi>Folio,</hi>
by procurement of his Church and Friends, and by his own Approbation before his
Death, that theſe his <hi>Chriſtian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Labours</hi> might be
Preſerved in the World. This <hi>Folio</hi> contains ten of his Excellent
<hi>Manuſcripts,</hi> prepared for the Preſs, before his Death; and ten of
his <hi>Choice Books</hi> already Printed, but long ago grown ſcarce, and not
now to be had. Their Titles are as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <list>
                     <item> 
                        <label>MANUSCRIPTS.</label> 1. <hi>An Expoſition of the Ten
firſt Chapters of</hi> Geneſis. 2. <hi>Juſtification by imputed
Righteouſneſs.</hi> 3. Paul<hi>'s Departure and Crown.</hi> 4.
Iſrael<hi>'s Hope Incouraged.</hi> 5. <hi>Deſires of the Righteous
granted.</hi> 6. <hi>The Saints Priviledge and Profit.</hi> 7. <hi>Chriſt a
Compleat Saviour.</hi> 8. <hi>Saints Knowledge of Chriſt's Love.</hi> 9.
<hi>The Houſe of the Foreſt of</hi> Lebanon. 10. <hi>A Deſcription
of</hi> Antichriſt.</item>
                     <item> 
                        <label>BOOKS formerly Printed.</label> 11. <hi>Saved by
Grace.</hi> 12. <hi>Chriſtian Behaviour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> 13. <hi>A Diſcourſe of
Prayer.</hi> 14. <hi>The Stait Gate.</hi> 15. <hi>Goſpel Truths opened.</hi>
16. <hi>Light for them in Darkneſs.</hi> 17. <hi>Inſtructions for the
Ignorant.</hi> 18. <hi>A Map of Salvation,</hi> &amp;c. 19. <hi>The</hi> New
Jeruſalem. 20. <hi>The Reſurrection.</hi> Price Bound 14<hi>s.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Mellificium Chirurgicae:</hi> Or, The Marrow of
Chyrurgery. An Anatomical Treatiſe. Inſtitutions of Phyſick, with
<hi>Hypocrates</hi>'s Aphoriſms largely Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented upon. The Marrow of
Phyſick, ſhewing the Cauſes, Signs and Cures of moſt Diſeaſes
incident to Human Bodies. Choice Experienced Receipts for the Cure of ſeveral
Diſtempers. The Fourth Edition, enlarged with many Additions, and purged from
many Faults that eſcaped in the former Impreſſions. Illuſtrated in its
ſeveral Parts with Twelve Braſs Cuts. By <hi>James Cooke</hi> of
<hi>Warwick,</hi> Practitioner in Phyſick and Chyrurgery. <hi>Price
Bound</hi> 6<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>Otto Tachenius</hi> his <hi>Hippocrates Chymicus,</hi>
diſcovering the Ancient Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the late <hi>Viperine Salt,</hi> with
his <hi>Clavis</hi> thereunto annexed; Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated by <hi>J. W.</hi> Price
Bound 3 3<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> Select Obſervations on Engliſh Bodies of Eminent
Perſons in deſperate Diſeaſes. Firſt Written in <hi>Latin</hi> by Mr.
<hi>John Hall,</hi> Phyſitian: After Engliſhed by <hi>James Cooke,</hi>
Author of the <hi>Marrow of Chyrurgery.</hi> To which is now added, an hundred
like <hi>Counſels</hi> and <hi>Advices,</hi> for ſeveral Honourable
Perſons; with all the ſeveral Medicines and Methods by which the ſeveral
Cures, by the Bleſſing of God, were effected; and they be of great uſe to
ſeveral Practitioners in Phyſick and others; by the ſame Author. In the
Cloſe is added, directions for drinking of the <hi>Bath-Water,</hi> and
<hi>Ars Coſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica,</hi> or Beautifying Art: By <hi>H. Stubs,</hi>
Phyſitian at <hi>Warwick.</hi> Price Bound 2<hi>s.</hi> 6.<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98510:5"/>
            <head>BOOKS lately Printed in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s
Works.</head>
            <list>
               <item>A Conciliatory Judgment concerning Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s
SERMONS, and Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> diſſatisfaction in them; by Mr.
<hi>Beverley,</hi> Price 2<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> A Conciliatory Diſcourſe upon Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s
Sermons on the Obſervation of Mr. <hi>William</hi>'s diſſatisfaction in
them, in which the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt in the Covenant of Grace:
Paſſing Knowledge is that which is aſpired to be made known; by Mr.
<hi>Beverly,</hi> price 6<hi>d:</hi>
               </item>
               <item> The True State of Goſpel-Truth, eſtabliſhed upon the
Free Election of God in Chriſt, the agreement and yet difference between Law
and Goſpel. So that the Goſpel cannot be ſtiled Law, the
inconditionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Goſpel Salvation. the precedure of the Day of
Judgment, in the way of a Conſiliatory Diſcourſe upon Mr.
<hi>Williams</hi> his Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: By Mr. <hi>Beverly.</hi> price
6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> Chriſt made Sin, from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. Evinct from
Scripture, upon occaſion of an Exception taken at <hi>Pinners-Hall,</hi> at
Reprinting of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Sermons: By <hi>Samuel Criſp</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> a Son of the ſaid Dr <hi>Criſp.</hi> price bound
2<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> Chriſt alone Exalted in Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Sermons; in
Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Daniel Williams:</hi> By <hi>S. Criſp</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> price 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> A Plain and Impartial Inquiry into Goſpel-Truth;
Eſpecially in reference to the Doctrine of Juſtification; In anſwer to Mr
<hi>Williams:</hi> By <hi>Thomas Edwards</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> price
1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> A Short Review of ſome Reflections, made by a Nameleſs
Author upon Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Sermons: With ſome Remarks upon the Union
and the Late Agreement in Doctrine among the Diſſenting Miniſters in
<hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don:</hi> By <hi>Thomas Edwards</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> price
6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Works, Entituled, <hi>Chriſt alone
Exalted:</hi> Containing 42 Sermons on ſeveral Select Texts of Scripture,
which were formerly Printed in three ſmall Volumes: To which is now added ten
Sermons, eight whereof were never before Printed: Faithfully Tranſlated from
his own Notes. Price Bound 8<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Where you may likewiſe be ſupplyed with what Dr.
<hi>Chauncy</hi> has writ in Vindication of Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi>'s Works.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> Correct theſe ERRATA<hi>'s</hi> with thy
Pen, or any other that may occur.</head>
            <p>PAg. 4. l. 24. before <hi>a Moral</hi> read <hi>was.</hi> p. 5. l.
28. for <hi>ſins charged</hi> r. <hi>ſin charged.</hi> p. 8. l. 24. r.
<hi>Mic.</hi> 5.5. p. 13. l. 22. r. <hi>Pemble.</hi> l. 25. for
<hi>believers</hi> r. <hi>a believer.</hi> l. 30. for <hi>as Conſonant</hi>
r. <hi>as far as Conſonant.</hi> l. 31. for <hi>and rejected</hi> r. <hi>or
rejected.</hi> p. 15. l. 28. r. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. p. 17. l. 14. r. <hi>Is it
becauſe it is ſaid.</hi> l. 30. for <hi>follow</hi> r. <hi>folly.</hi> p.
24. l. 3. for <hi>deſires</hi> r. <hi>defines.</hi> l. 23. <hi>after
ſo</hi> r. <hi>they.</hi> p. 25. l. 8. for <hi>that</hi> r. <hi>the.</hi> l.
13. r. <hi>abſtractly.</hi> p. 28. l. 40. for <hi>one</hi> r. <hi>thing.</hi>
p. 29. l. 16. r. <hi>for refuge.</hi> p. 31. l. 1. r. <hi>and the like
hardly.</hi> l. 19. r. <hi>ſeeing it was grounded.</hi> l. 35. for
<hi>and</hi> r. <hi>to.</hi> p. 34. l. 35. r. <hi>Pemble.</hi> p. 38. l. 21. r.
<hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1,2. p. 43. l. 35. r. proofs. p. 48. l. 21. for <hi>but</hi> r.
<hi>on.</hi> p. 50. l. 6. r. <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> p. 51. l. 41. for <hi>it
toucheth</hi> r. <hi>touch.</hi> p. 56. l. 12. before <hi>in the
preſence</hi> dele <hi>and.</hi> l. 22 r. <hi>for whoſe ſake God.</hi> p.
59. l. 38. for <hi>yea</hi> r. <hi>yet.</hi> p. 61. l. ult. r.
<hi>primary.</hi> p. 63. l. 33. r. <hi>not of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98510:5"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE Firſt Sermon.</head>
            <p>THE firſt Crime that is laid to Doctor <hi>Criſps</hi> Charge,
is that he calls the matter about which he is ſpeaking, to wit, The bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits
of Chriſt: 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Hidden Manna,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Marrow and Fatneſs.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Admirable Muſick to the Heart.</hi> And,</item>
                  <item>IV. To have <hi>An Inebriating Vertue.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Expreſſions Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> calls <hi>ſtrains of
Rhetorick,</hi> and <hi>Enticeing Words of Mans Wiſdom,</hi> &amp;c. with
many other bitter words; whereas indeed they are the very Expreſſions of
the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>For the Firſt; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>will give to
his people of the hidden Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> Rev. 2.17. which cannot be meant of any
thing but of the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Himſelf and his Benefits.</p>
            <p>So Secondly, <hi>David,</hi> in the 63 Pſalm, after he had
ſaid, That <hi>the Loving kindneſs of the Lord is better than Life,</hi> in
the 3d. Verſe: He adds in the 5th. Verſe, That <hi>his Soul is filled as it
were with Marrow and Fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> namely, in the enjoyment of that loving
kindneſs which is only manifeſted in his Son. So when the Prophet
<hi>Eſay</hi> foretells the times of Chriſt, chap. 25. ver. 6,7. <hi>When
the Lord will deſtroy the face of the cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt upon all people,</hi>
then <hi>he will make unto all people a Feaſt of Fat things, a feaſt of
Wines on the Lees, of fat things full of Marrow.</hi> Which, with out all
doubt, is the glorious Feaſt of the Goſpel, and the Benefits therein
publiſhed unto the World.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That he calls the ſame Doctrine <hi>Muſick,</hi> is
not an unuſual metaphor to the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>We have Piped unto you,</hi>
ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98510:6"/> ye have not Danced,</hi> Mat.
11.17. And what did all thoſe Inſtruments of Muſick in the Old
Teſtament repreſent, but the delight that came by the preaching of the
Goſpel, which cauſed great Joy whereſoever it came? The <hi>Eunuch,</hi>
after he had learnt it, went on his way Rejoycing, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.39. And upon
the preaching of it by <hi>Philip,</hi> there was <hi>great Joy in the City
of</hi> Samaria, <hi>Act.</hi> 8.8. But the laſt expreſſion, that it hath
an <hi>inebriating vertue,</hi> is moſt urged and excepted againſt; which
yet the Holy Ghoſt will own, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 1.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>drink and be inebriated O my
Beloved ones;</hi> ſo the beſt Tranſlations extant have rendred it,
<hi>viz.</hi> the Greek Septuagint, <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremellius</hi> in
Latine, and our laſt Engliſh in the Margin. And they are the very ſame
words (though ſpoken in a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual ſenſe) with thoſe ſaid of
<hi>Noah,</hi> that he <hi>drank of the Wine, and was drunken,</hi> Gen. 9.21.
neither is it unuſual for the Holy Ghoſt to draw compariſons from things
which are Vitious in themſelves, which in the ſpiritual ſenſe of the
ſcripture are nothing ſo. <hi>Behold I come,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>as
a Theif in the Night.</hi> Whereby, I hope, Chriſt doth neither draw any
ſtain of that Vice upon himſelf, nor encourage, nor maintain it in others.
So although the beloved ones of Chriſt are ſaid to be <hi>inebriated</hi>
with the ſenſe of the overflowing of the Lords grace and mercy upon them,
yet thereby is not ſignified any vicious diſtemper in them, or any
patroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of that loathſom ſin of carnal drunkenneſs in others.</p>
            <p>But more of this it may be at the 16 <hi>Sect.</hi> of the 4th.
<hi>Sermon;</hi> all which he ſpends in exagitating this phraſe: Only for
the preſent I deſire the Godly Reader to take notice what an indignity is
offered to the Holy Ghoſt, that his words ſhould be called the <hi>Enticing
words of Mans wiſdom.</hi> Neither can he evade by ſaying, that he had
reference to the Drs. mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contained under thoſe words; for it muſt be
words not meaning, that he calls enticing words. And I believe himſelf will
not deny that it was the very word <hi>inebriate,</hi> which he excepted ſo
againſt.</p>
            <p>In the 2, 3, &amp; 4 Sections, there is not any matter of moment,
but falſe accuſations without proof, and reviling words, whereof his whole
Book is full, to which any indifferent Reader will bear me witneſs: Whereunto
our Anſwer ſhall be only to beſeech the Lord, that they may not be layd
to his charge. That the Dr. any where ſpeaks againſt <hi>humble, obedient,
and ſanctified ſpirits,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> charges him in
<hi>Sect.</hi> 2. I doubt not but the contrary will be made evidently to appear
by his own words, when they come to be ſcanned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. For the perfect diſcharge of Gods people from
the fault and guilt of ſin, the Dr. urged <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. <hi>Waſh
thou me, and I ſhall be whiter than ſnow.</hi> Here. Mr. <hi>Geree,</hi>
although he confeſſeth the truth of the Doctrine, <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. yet he
ſuppoſeth that he hath gotten a double advantage.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Dr. <hi>alledgeth Texts out of the Old
Teſtament, which</hi> (as he ſaith) <hi>we will not admit of in matter of
juſtification.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98510:6"/>2. That <hi>David in this Text prays for
forgiveneſs of ſins; which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is contrary to the</hi>
Antinomian <hi>Tenet:</hi> To theſe Two briefly.</p>
            <p>To the Firſt, concerning the ſtate and condition of the Old
Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I confeſs there is ſome difficulty, and almoſt in all Ages
ſince Chriſt, there hath been ſome diſpute about it. I ſhall not
enter into any large diſcourſe, as not being ſuitable to our preſent
occaſion. Onely becauſe we have been exceedingly ſlandered, and that by
ſome in pulpits, (when men ſtand to ſpeak in the Name of the God of
Truth, and therefore ſhould have been ſo wary as not to ſpeak a word, but
what the God of Truth would own for his) that we denyed the whole Law; by
others, that we denyed all the Old Teſtament; and by others, that we deny the
whole Scriptures: I ſhall briefly expreſs what we hold in this matter, and
leave it to the judgment of the godly-wiſe to be examined by, and judged of
according to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We do, and have always acknowledged the
<hi>whole Scriptures,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>to be by Divine
Inſpiration: And the Old and New Teſtament both of them to be of equal and
indiſputable Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We acknowledge, That <hi>all the People of God
in the time of the Old Testament, were equally juſtified before God, and
ſaved with thoſe in the New; And that by that one and onely means of
juſtification before God and Salvation, even Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous,
who in that reſpect, is the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for
ever,</hi> Heb. 13. Hitherto I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there is an Agreement. All the reſt,
and that wherein the difference lyeth, I ſhall ſumm up in this third
Concluſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We ſay, <hi>That the whole Administration and
Diſpenſation of the Old Teſtament, ſo far as it. was typical, ought not
to be urged upon the Children of the New Teſtament.</hi> And even in this
Concluſion, as it lyes <hi>in Theſi,</hi> and in the general there will be
little or no difference; only in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> and in particular, and
in explaining how far this old Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration was typical, there may be
ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ariety of Judgments, which
is a great cauſe, as I conceive, of the being and continuation of the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent differences.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Therefore to diſcern how far the
Adminiſtrations of the Old Teſtament were typical, I conceive there is not
a more ſure and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Rule than this, namely, 
<note place="margin">☜</note>That <hi>where any thing peculiar
and proper un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt alone is attributed unto any action, perſon, or
thing, whether Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monial or Moral, that Attribution is to be accounted
Typical, and to relate unto that action, perſon or thing, only as they were
types and ſhadows of Chriſt to come: And therefore Christ being already
come, now in the times of the New Teſtament, no ſuch Attribution ought to
be given unto them,</hi> although they be of ſuch a nature, as that they
remain in uſe alſo ſince Chriſt's time, becauſe that typical
adminiſtration is wholly ceaſed. I deſire to be fully underſtood, and
therefore ſhall explain my ſelf a little further. Obſerve therefore;</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98510:7"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Adminiſtrations of
the Old Teſtament, were of things which were of themſelves of ſeveral
natures; ſome were Ceremonial, as the Sacrifices, their Temples, their
Tabernacles, their Altars, and ſuch like; ſome were Moral, as their
Prayers, Repentance, Reformations, and all the Duties of the Moral Law.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> that they were Types of Chriſt, and
ſo ceaſed by the coming of the ſubſtance Chriſt himſelf, is
generally acknowledged; onely ſome attribute unto them no efficacy at all,
but only a ſhaddow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Chriſt and his benefits, who was to come;
others ſay they had a typical, carnal, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mporal efficiency, in the Moſaical Church and Common-wealth,
proper to that Adminiſtration, and anſwerable in ſome way to the benefits
in the New: That they by the Ordinance of God brought down upon that People
temporal and outward bleſſings anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſpiritual and eternal
bleſſings by Chriſt. Which Queſtion is largely diſcuſſed by
<hi>Voſſius,</hi> wherein I ſhall not interpoſe, becauſe they that
attribute moſt unto thoſe Ceremonial performances, yet bound the effect of
them within the compaſs of the Old Teſtament, ſo that they reſigned up
their keyes and power unto their Lord and King (whoſe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bingers they were)
at his appearing.</p>
            <p>But for the Actions and Adminiſtrations of the <hi>Moral
Law,</hi> that they alſo were in ſome ſort typical, is not ſo uſually
obſerved as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; yet it is no leſs true. Who can deny but that
<hi>Phineas</hi> his pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or executing of juſtice, whether ſoever it
was (for the Hebrew will probably bear either) a Moral Action, and yet
typically ſhadowing out unto us Chriſt our Great High-Prieſt, by whoſe
interceding for us with the Father, he is pacified towards us? So not a few
Proteſtant Writers have interpreted it. But what ſpeak I of one Action,
when as Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi> hath publiſhed a Book wherein he diſcovers all
along a Typical ſhadowing forth of Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not only in the
<hi>Ceremonial,</hi> but alſo <hi>Moral</hi> Actions of moſt of the Antient
Patriarcks, Prieſts, Judges, Kings and Prophets. But here I do not deſire
to diſpute the Queſtion, but only as briefly as I can to explain my
Judgment. Therefore in ſuch Moral Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as theſe, I obſerve Three
Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Their <hi>Moral Nature</hi> whereby they are of
perpetual uſe both in the time of the Old Teſtament and of the New; as
Prayer, Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and other Actions of Duty towards God and man are as
neceſſary as ever they were in the time of the Old Teſtament, and ſhall
be by the true Children of Faith as much practiſed, and in a more ſpiritual
manner contrary to that falſe ſlander that paſſeth abroad concerning
us, That we let men looſe from all duties of piety towards God, or charity
towards man; againſt which falſe reproaches the Lord will in time ariſe
to the Vindication of his People. In the mean time, they may be bold to commend
their names and reputations unto Him into whoſe hands they have already
committed their ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98510:7"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In theſe actions there is
their <hi>typical effect,</hi> whereby, if they were good Actions in that
Adminiſtration, they wrought propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable effects, as <hi>Phineas</hi> his
praying ſtayed the plague: If they were evil actions, they brought evil
effects, as <hi>David's</hi> numbring the People brought the plague; his
Adultery the death of the Child, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe effects I call
typical, becauſe they are attributed to theſe actions, as they do typically
relate unto Chriſt, and ſetting aſide that relation, ſuch an effect
ſhould not have been attributed unto them. As for Example, the prayer of
<hi>Phineas</hi> had not ſtayd the plague, if he had not therein ſtood as a
Type of Chriſt, who is the onely one that turns away all evil from thoſe
that are his, who becauſe he was not ſo reveal'd in thoſe times,
therefore it was requiſite that it ſhould be ſhaddowed out unto them in
this and ſuch like Types; ſo that the effect is only aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the
Type <hi>in umbra</hi> in the ſhadow, but to the thing typified <hi>in
veritate</hi> in the truth. So I think I may ſay that all actions, even of
the Moral Law, do in this manner point unto Chriſt. In like ſort,
<hi>David</hi>'s Adultery brought the death of the Child, as the typical effect
of that ſin: So that <hi>David</hi> in that conſideration bare his own
ſin; But how? Onely as a Type of Chriſt, as manifeſting that the Saviour
of the World that was to bear their ſins, was yet to come. Yet did he not
really bear his own ſin, no not in any degree: For ſo it was wholly
reſerved for the Lord Chriſt, upon whom it was charged to the uttermoſt,
who made a full ſatisfaction, not only for the eternal, but alſo the
temporal puniſhment of all that belong unto him, not only for thoſe ſince
Chriſt, but even for all from the beginning of the world: ſo that neither
<hi>David,</hi> nor any other of the Children of God in the Old Teſtament,
had ever had any ſins charged on them, had they not ſtood as Types of him
that was to come to bear the ſins of many; neither ever had they ſins
charged upon them in the real poſitive nature of it, (if I may ſo ſpeak)
for ſo it was only and wholly born by Chriſt for them; but onely as I
ſaid in this typical conſideration: <hi>For Chriſt onely hath with one
ſacrifice perfected for ever thoſe that are conſecrated,</hi> Heb. 10.14.
<hi>He onely is the propitiation for our ſins,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.1,2. And this
he did not onely for thoſe ſince Chriſt, but alſo for <hi>the ſins
that were past,</hi> Rom. 3.25. to wit, under the former Covenant,
<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. So then in the time of the New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſince the death
of Chriſt, there is no remembrance of ſin, neither upon Chriſt who is
riſen again from the dead without ſin, nor upon the faithful, ſeeing they
cannot now be ſhadows of Chriſt to come, who is already come, and by the
luſtre of his preſence, hath made all ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows flee away.</p>
            <p>So that the whole amounteth to that which I layd down in the
begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, namely, <hi>That where any thing is attributed to perſons or
actions, which is Chriſts own peculiar, that is to be underſtood of thoſe
perſons or actions, onely as they do typically relate unto Chriſt, and
ought not to be aſcribed <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98510:8"/> to any other perſon or action
(though otherwiſe of the ſame kind) which have not this typical relation
unto Chriſt.</hi> The Reaſon is taken from that main foundation of
Chriſtian Religion, to wit, The ſatisfaction of Chriſt is compleat, and
all the Scriptures hold it forth as All-ſufficient and compleat.</p>
            <p>Thus have I, Chriſtian Reader, given thee a ſhort abridgment
of my thoughts concerning the difference of the Teſtaments, ſo far as it
concerns the preſent matter in debate, and as the preſent occaſion would
permit, being willing rather to treſpaſs upon thee by this digreſſion,
than to ſuffer this matter altogether to paſs untouched, being of ſuch
moment, both for the Vindication of the Truth and Us from ſo many ſlanders:
Hereafter, if God permit, I may have an opportunity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain my ſelf more
largely in this matter, and to ſhew the conſonancy thereof, both to the
current of the Scriptures, and alſo to the beſt and moſt Orthodox
Proteſtant Writers. Now to Mr. <hi>Geree</hi>'s Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To the Firſt, that the Dr. <hi>alledgeth places out of
the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> I Anſwer ſo he may, ſo as that he alledge none
proper to the Old Adminiſtration, as many do to bring the Children of the New
Teſtament into the ſame ſervile condition with thoſe of the Old, who
albeit they were Sons, and thereby truly Heirs of Life and Glory, and as the
Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Lords of all:</hi> Yet in regard of that ſubſervient
Covenant and Adminiſtration, they differed nothing at all from ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants.
But onely ſuch Scriptures as do propheſy and foretell the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of
Chriſt, and the glory that ſhould follow, ſuch as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
mentioned are. Although a man may not alledge the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, (as I doubt
not but Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> will confeſs) for circumciſion and obſervation
of the Jewiſh Sabbath, or ſacrificing beaſts: Yet may he alledge it, to
prove, that Chriſt is the ſubſtance, exhibiting unto the Children of the
New Teſtament all that was ſhadowed out by theſe Ceremonies. Now there is
the ſame reaſon of the whole Moſaical Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration. So ſaith
<hi>Pareus</hi> upon <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.3. <hi>By the Elements of the world,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>the Apoſtle understandeth not onely the Ceremonies, but the
whole polity of</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Levitical Prieſthood, and the very
Moral Law it ſelf affrighting them, and compelling them to Obedience with
threatnings of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the fear of the Curſe.</hi> How proves he
this? <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Chriſt is ſaid a little after to have
delivered his Church from all theſe. And therefore all theſe muſt be
understood by the Elements of the world and bondage.</hi> In a word, although
the Old Teſtament may not be urged upon the faithful, as eſtabliſhing the
Old Covenant, yet it may as fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telling the New.</p>
            <p>His other Advantage he thinks he hath got by the Example urged,
is, That <hi>David though juſtified prayed for forgiveneſs,</hi> which he
ſaith we deny. Where or when? O Mr. <hi>Geree,</hi> you pretend you have
matter <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98510:8"/> enough in the Book to confute, and do you leave that
and run after ſlanders of your own deviſing? This may well be put up on the
file of thoſe falſe and injurious reproaches which we dayly lye under: For
the contrary hath been publickly delivered by us both in print and pulpit,
namely, That the <hi>faithful and juſtified are to pray for forgiveneſs of
ſins,</hi> according as Chriſt hath taught. Onely this we ſay with the
beſt Proteſtant Writers, that forgiveneſs is to be underſtood, not of
that <hi>in foro Coeli,</hi> in the Court of Heaven, which prevents and goes
before all our prayers; but <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> in the Court of
our own Conſciences. That we may more and more have the fruition and
enjoyment in our Conſciences, of that forgiveneſs eſtabliſhed in Heaven
before. And ſo is that Petition of the Lords Prayer to be underſtood,
according to Mr. <hi>Walker</hi> in his <hi>Socinianiſm diſcovered,</hi>
pag. But the truth is, men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of true Chriſtian Love, which
thinketh no evil, have made their own Uncharitable Collections from our Tenets,
and then fathered thoſe Collections upon us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. To evince the perfection of our juſtification
the Dr. cited, (as is uſual in extemporary expreſſions) according to the
matter, though not exactly according to the words, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.25. and ſo
forward, that <hi>Chriſt preſents his Church to himſelf not having ſpot
or wrinkle;</hi> wherein he takes notice that the Participle, <hi>[not having
ſpot]</hi> is of the preſent tenſe, and therefore it is not onely to be
underſtood of their future eſtate in the Life to come. <hi>This
Teſtimony,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Geree, is clear againſt him.</hi> How can
that be I pray you? His Point he deſires to prove by this Text, is the
perfection of our juſtification, which Point, ſaith Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> in
the laſt words of the former Section, is granted. How then can this Scripture
be clear againſt it, or againſt him if not againſt it? Is one truth of
Scripture clear againſt another? Yea, but he <hi>cites it,</hi> ſaith Mr.
<hi>G. for justification, when as it is ſpecial for ſanctification.</hi>
See what a Reaſon is given here. Is it therefore clearly contrary to
juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it is ſpecially for ſanctification? He dares
not deny but it toucheth alſo upon juſtification. And if it did but ſo, I
hope it doth not in that touch ſhew juſtification to be imperfect, but
rather perfect and without ſpot; if ſo, how is it then againſt the Dr.
who alledgeth it to that purpoſe? Doth the Dr. deny that they have reference
to ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication alſo? No, but he urgeth them onely for juſtification,
becauſe that was the matter onely in hand. <hi>But the words are not in the
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe.</hi> What Words?
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>that he might
preſent.</hi> Did he ſay it was? No, but
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not having ſpot:</hi> I
hope that is the preſent tenſe. Yea, ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi> but when was
this to be in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe? Even, ſaith he, when it was preſented
glorious, that is in Heaven, as Interpreters expound it; See <hi>Piſcat. in
locum.</hi> But is it only to be expounded of the eſtate of God's Children in
Heaven? I think he <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98510:9"/> dares not affirm it: And if not, why may
it not alſo ſignifie our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleatneſs here on earth, whereby we are
ſaid to be compleat in him even in this life? <hi>Col.</hi> 2.10. Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> might have noted, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Aoriſt</hi> noting the time paſt, having cleanſed
us, will rather evince, that the ſpotleſsneſs which immediately follows
upon the cleanſing, is paſt, than barely future in Heaven.</p>
            <p>In the Conference at the <hi>Hague,</hi> the <hi>Arminians</hi>
ſay, that this is their Judgment, That to be Holy and without blame before
God, is the ſame with, to be glorified in Heaven, in this place,
<hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26,27. To which purpoſe they urge <hi>Piſcater,</hi> as
Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> doth here. Whereunto <hi>Ameſius</hi> anſwereth in his
<hi>Coronis, Artic.</hi> 1 <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 12. That <hi>the ſanctification ſpoken of,</hi> (by which
word Mr. <hi>G.</hi> thinks he hath gotten ſomething) <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends not
onely Renovation but alſo Juſtification,</hi> as <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.17.
<hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Becauſe,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>the whole fruit of the love and death of Chriſt is placed in
that ſanctification, which cannot be contained within the bounds of Heaven,
but preſenteth the Church marryed unto him without ſpot, even whilſt
ſhe ſojourneth and warreth here on earth.</hi> And for <hi>Piſcator,</hi>
he anſwereth, <hi>That he doth not onely limit it to the ſtate in Heaven,
but ſpeaks upon verſe</hi> 26. (in Analyſ.) <hi>of that cleanſing which
conſists in remiſſion of ſins.</hi> And to this ſame purpoſe have
many other approved Writers cited this Text, and thoſe parallel to it. As the
Holy Martyr <hi>Frith</hi> (<hi>pag.</hi> 69.70.) againſt <hi>Raſtal,</hi>
where he ſaith, That <hi>they to whom God im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth not their ſins, are
bleſſed, righteous, without ſpot, wrinkle or blame.</hi> And Mr.
<hi>Ellis</hi> before the Parliament, upon <hi>Micah</hi> 55. <hi>pag.</hi> 17.
where he hath theſe faithful words, <hi>That God is reconciled by the blood
of his Son, which takes away all ſin, ſo clearly, that it leaves no ſpot
or wrinkle, no blame or accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that it being applyed by Faith, God
himſelf hath nothing to lay to our Charge, but we have full peace with him,
and joy and glory in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But poor man,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>Geree, he took it upon
truſt; for his Mr.</hi> Eaton <hi>takes it just ſo in his Honey-comb, of
whom he hath borrowed moſt of his New Divinity.</hi> O Mr. <hi>Geree,</hi>
where was the gravity of your ſilver hair, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Miniſter of
Chriſt, when ſuch light taunting, jeering ſtuff fell from your pen,
againſt a man ſo free from all gall and bitterneſs towards any Friends or
Foes, as thus againſt the Laws of Common Humanity, to rend up the ſepulchre
of the dead, and to trample upon his bones? Know therefore, that although it is
not, neither did he account it any diſparagement to learn from the meaneſt,
much leſs from Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi> whoſe Name ſhall be had in
Everlaſting Remembrance among the truly Faithful, though you mention him
frequently with ſo much ſcorn: Yet he had both learned and preached
abundantly this faithful Doctrine of God's Free Grace, which you after your
ſcoffing manner call New Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, not onely before any thing of Mr.
<hi>Eatons</hi> was extant, but even before he had ſo much as heard of his
Name.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:98510:9"/>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. Whereas the blind World
uſually is wont to gather falſe Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences from true and ſound
premiſes, they according to the principle that is within them, underſtand
that carnally which is ſpoken ſpiritually: Therefore the Dr. here by
Anſwering an Objection, prevents a ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Inference that ſome made
through the miſunderſtanding of his former doctrine of our compleatneſs
before God in Juſtification, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they were ready to infer that he
denyed that Believers do ſin. And that becauſe he aſſerted a perfection
in the Spirit and in Chriſt; he muſt needs alſo grant a perfection in the
fleſh, and in works, as the Papiſts and Familiſts would have it. For
although they both of them call their perfection which they dream of, a
perfection in Chriſt, yet in deed and in truth, if it be diligently ſifted,
it will to truly ſpiritual eyes, appear to be onely a perfection made up of
works and inherent qualities. But this is not the buſineſs in hand, onely I
deſire to give the faithful an intimation, leaſt by any means their minds
ſhould be drawn away from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt. Now to the
Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Dr. Anſwers, that even the Faithful, if conſidered in the
doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of works, do commit ſin, and the truth is, in themſelves, they do
nothing elſe but commit ſin. If they have any thing they have received it,
if they do any thing that is good, it is to be aſcribed to the Spirit of God,
not to them who of themſelves do nothing but ſin, their ſouls being even
mints of ſin. This is the ſubſtance of his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> Mr. <hi>G.</hi> (<hi>Serm.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect.</hi>
19.) ſaith, <hi>it ſeemed very ſtrange to him, till he found the ſame
in Mr.</hi> Eaton. But why did it ſeem ſo ſtrange? You might have
conſidered that the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> calls <hi>all our
Righteouſneſs as a menſtruous cloath, Iſa.</hi> 64.6. whereby not onely
ſin, but the extream fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſs of ſin is expreſſed. And that the
Apoſtle counted all things but dung and loſs, that he might gain Chriſt,
among which things he reckons all his own righteouſneſs, to wit, of works,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8,9. And that of Chriſt, who teacheth us to confeſs our
beſt performances, even when we have done that which is commanded us, to be
but unprofitable ſervice. Oh what are they then, when nothing is done as it
was commanded to be done! May we not truly ſay with <hi>Bernard,</hi> Hom. 5.
<hi>If all our very righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſes being looked upon by the light of
Truth, be found to be as menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rags, what then ſhall our
unrighteouſneſs be accounted to be? If the light that is in us be
darkneſs, how great then is our darkneſs?</hi> I doubt not but that if Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> had conſidered theſe Expreſſions of the Holy Ghoſt, that
of the Doctor's would not have ſeemed altogether ſo ſtrange unto him. But
it is true which Learned <hi>Chamier</hi> ſaith upon the ſame occaſion.
For when <hi>Calvin</hi> had ſaid, <hi>That no work comes from the Saints
which doth not deſerve the juſt reward of ſhame and confuſion,</hi>
Inſt. l. 3. c. 14. Sect. 9. And <hi>Luther,</hi> That <hi>the juſt man
ſins in every good work, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98510:10"/> all good
works are ſo many venial ſins, and venial not in their own nature,
according to the Popiſh Definition, but onely by the Mercy of God,</hi> Cham.
Tom. 3. lib. And theſe places of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> with
ſuch like of other Proteſtant Writers, when as ſome Papiſt, as Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> doth here, did exceedingly reſent and think ſtrange;
<hi>Chamier</hi> anſwereth, <hi>That it is no wonder if ſuch
expreſſions ſeem ſtrange and horrid unto them, who uſed and delighted
to hear nothing but the high-prizing and advancing of their own Works.</hi> If
this be not the ſame diſeaſe that Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and ſome others are
ſick of, I am deceived. But let us go on and hear this learned mans
Reſolution of this Queſtion, which I ſhall the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther recite, becauſe
he proves his Concluſion by an Unanſwerable De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration from the Word
it ſelf in the fore-cited place, <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. <hi>Good Works,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>may be two wayes conſidered, either abſtractly in that
nature, and according to thoſe dimenſions of Goodneſs which they ought to
have; or concretely, that is, not in that ſimple nature and conſideration
of Goodneſs, but as they are cloathed with circumſtances, and as they are
done by that nature whereby they are done.</hi> Having premiſed this
di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, he proceeds in the 6th. <hi>Section</hi> to his concluſion or
aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with the proof of it. <hi>We affirm,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that
ſuch is the frailty of Humane nature, corrupted with ſin, that no ſuch
works can be given, that were ever done by any meer man, which do not decline
more or leſs from the exact rule of Gods Law. And becauſe ſin is defined
to be</hi> (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> exorbitatio a lege)
<hi>a tranſgreſſion of the Law, it must neceſſarily follow, that
theſe works which do thus deflect from their rule, are ſins.</hi> And in
like manner <hi>Auguſtine</hi> of old concluded, That it is ſin, either
<hi>when there is no Charity, or when it is leſs than it ought to be.</hi>
Now in our beſt Works, I hope, it will be granted by all that are truly
Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, that there is leſs Charity, leſs Love of GOD and Man, than
there ought to be. So then, I hope, here are ſome before Mr. <hi>Eaton,</hi>
who have affirmed, The beſt that we do, to be ſin.</p>
            <p>But what hath Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> to the contrary. <hi>He
conceiveth that of Paul,</hi> Rom. 7.12. <hi>to be againſt us, ſo then with
my mind I (my ſelf) ſerve the Law of God, but with my fleſh the Law of
ſin.</hi> But how did he ſerve the Law of God? By performing all or any one
Action without declining from it even in that Action? No ſuch matter. He
himſelf in the ſame place confeſſeth the clean contrary. How, ſaith
he, to perform that which is good I find not. And the good that I would I do
not, but the evil which I would not, that do I. How then did he ſerve the Law
of God will you ſay? Read and obſerve the whole current of that Chapter,
that he never arrogates unto himſelf that ſervice of the Law which
conſiſts in performing of it, or that which is good according to it, but
onely by an acknowledgment that the Law was <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98510:10"/> 
               <hi>holy,
juſt, and good, and ſpiritual,</hi> ver. 12,14,16. This is all I can find
the Apoſtle challenging to himſelf all along that Chapter. Now whereas it
might be objected againſt Mr. <hi>G.</hi> the Apoſtle ſaith, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 15,10. as the Dr. doth here, <hi>Not I but the Grace of God
which was with me;</hi> He anſwereth, that <hi>the meaning is, Not he chiefly
or of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi> Which expoſition although it be true in ſome
ſence, yet is it not ſuitable to the matter in hand. It is true, I ſay,
that <hi>Paul</hi> was in ſome ſort active in this, labouring not onely in
the work it ſelf, but alſo in the goodneſs of it, ſo far as the
goodneſs of it is kept here below, and commends us for good among men. But if
we aſcend higher, and bring it before the Tribunal of God, ſo it had no
good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs but what is paſſive and imputed, it needed forgiveneſs of
Sins. So that although <hi>Paul</hi> was opperative in the work, yet not
properly in the goodneſs of it; When I would do good, evil is preſent with
me, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. It is God that worketh both the will and the deed,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 2. In reference to which, <hi>Calvin</hi> (<hi>Inſt. lib.</hi>
2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.) Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues vehemently. <hi>We ſteal from
the Lord what we arrogate to our ſelves, either in will or deed.</hi> And
again, (<hi>Ibid. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3.) ſaith he,
<hi>we do not as the Sophiſters do, part the glory of good works between God
and man, but reſerve it whole and untouched unto the Lord. This only we
aſſigne unto man, that thoſe things which were good, he by his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity
doth pollute and defile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>G. This is contrary to John,</hi> 1
<hi>Joh.</hi> 3.9. <hi>He</hi> that is born of God ſinneth not;
<hi>which,</hi> ſaith he, Mr. <hi>Eaton expounds thus: He cannot chuſe but
wreſtle and ſtrive againſt all Sin, and Zealouſly follow
Holineſs.</hi> I anſwer, that ſuppoſing this expoſition, he cannot
evince that any thing we do is not Sin or Sinfull. <hi>Paul</hi> ſtrove and
wreſtled as it appears in that 7. to the <hi>Romans,</hi> yet he concludes,
that when he would do good, evil is preſent with him; and that how to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form that which is good, he finds not. It is one thing to ſtrive,
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other to attain; the one is the task of Works, the other the Crown of
Faith.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>G. If a Believer can do nothing but Sin, then
he muſt. needs be ſubject to the Law; For, Sin is the Tranſgreſſion
of the Law,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that Mr. <hi>G.</hi> is good at digreſſing and
running from his Subject. For Dr. <hi>Criſp</hi> hath no where medled with
this Queſtion. Againſt whom then doth he make this inference? Surely it
muſt be againſt him that was the firſt Author of that aſſertion, That
Believers are not ſubject to, or under the Law. Who was that? Even the Holy 
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98510:11"/> Ghoſt by <hi>Steven;</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> ſeven
times (as <hi>Whitaker</hi> obſerveth in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>Luther,</hi>
againſt whom the <hi>Papiſts</hi> exclaimed for the ſame thing)
affirmeth, that <hi>Believers are not under the Law, but under grace.</hi> And
to ſay truth, it is no new thing for them to be accounted
<hi>Antinomians,</hi> or Enemies to the Law, for theſe and ſuch like
ſayings: The Phariſees that were of Old, charged this ſame imputation
upon them. For <hi>Steven,</hi> he is charged to have <hi>ſpoken
blaſphemous words againſt the Law,</hi> Act. 6.13. And it was not without
cauſe that <hi>Paul</hi> was forced to Apologize. <hi>Do we then make void
the Law through Faith? God forbid, nay, we eſtabliſh the Law,</hi> Rom.
3.31. In like manner Mr. <hi>G.</hi> thinks he hath ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us in
the ſame matter; although he hath found nothing in the book concerning that
matter. In the preface indeed ſomthing is briefly ſpoken concerning our
judgment herein, whereunto although he pretends a virtual confutation, as he
calls it, yet the Chriſtian Reader may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that he hath not ſpoken
one ſyllable concerning this ſubject of the Law, which being the main
matter in the world, and in the front of Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. book, he ought not
to have baulked it, but either to have ſhewed that which is there ſpoken of
the Law to have been unſound, or elſe to have approved it.
Notwithſtanding, becauſe we deſire not to walk in darkneſs, I ſhall
more explain my Judgment herein.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We ſay that the Law (I mean the moral Law,
according to the Moſaical and typical adminiſtration of it, as it is as
<hi>Paraeus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-cited Saith, one of thoſe <hi>Elementa Mundi</hi>
under which the Church of God in the nonage of the Old Teſtament was) the Law
I ſay in that Adminiſtration is now ceaſed. To evince this, is the main
drift of the Apoſtle in the 3, 4, and 5. Chapters of the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Galathians,</hi> and in a great part of the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Hebrews,</hi> where <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. the whole Law is
called a ſhadow of good things to come; and in the 9. <hi>Chap. v.</hi> 19.
and 20. even the Moral Law is included within their Covenant, to wit, as it
ſtands in this Typical conſideration, not as a pure Covenant of works
unvailed, for ſo they were not able to bare it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſay, That the true Believer is not under
the Law in that higher ſenſe, as it is a pure unvailed covenant of Works.
So it is a yoke indeed, that neither we nor our fathers were able to bear,
<hi>Acts</hi> 15. ſo we are delivered from it by him that was made under the
Law, to redeem them that were under the Law, that we might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the
adoptions of ſons, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. Yet not by aboliſhing or making void
the law even in this ſenſe: For it remains an everlaſting covenant of
works in full force unto all that are under it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19. but only by
a peculiar exemption of a little flock from under it: Which exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion yet is
not without a full and compleat ſatisfaction exhibited to <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98510:11"/> the Law; ſo that it loſeth not one jot or tittle, no not by
thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted perſons; but rather is by the exemption more fully
eſtabliſhed. For a <hi>particular exemption,</hi> as the Lawyers ſpeak,
<hi>eſtabliſheth a Law;</hi> for where no Law is in force, there needs no
peculiar exemption. And Secondly, becauſe that exemption is grounded upon a
full and preſent Satisfaction to the Law: Whereas in regard of the perſons
not exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it muſt be a receiving ſatisfaction world without end, and
yet never have one in actual being, a preſent ſatisfaction. Even as a man
going out of the Kingdom, and ſo from under the Laws of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; the
Laws of the Kingdom are not aboliſhed or deſtroyed by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, but
remains in the ſame force as they were before: Eſpecially even in regard of
himſelf the Laws are no loſers, if he went not out without making a
ſufficient ſatisfaction to the Laws of the Kingdom for all duties and
ſervices which he ſhould owe thereunto; which is the very caſe of the
children of God in reference to the Law, as a covenant of Works. They are
tranſlated out of the Kingdom of the Law and Works, into the Kingdom of
Chriſt and of Grace, there to be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ordered and judged by the
perfect Law of Liberty, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Exemptions being premiſed, I ſee not but we may
admit of any other uſe of the Law in the Church which doth not make Void
either of theſe Exemptions; And particularly thoſe which are contained in
Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. preface collected out of Mr. <hi>Reinolds</hi> Mr.
<hi>Penible,</hi> and <hi>Luther,</hi> according to the Authors own genuine
meaning.</p>
            <p>And further that we may not contend about words, I ſhall alſo
grant the Law to be a Rule of converſation even to believers underſtanding
it materially, and in his Doctrine and Duties, and paſſively as a Rule
barely lying before a man. To conſtitute a Rule in this ſence, I
ſuppoſe no more is meant, but that if the actions and converſation of a
Child of God be examined before an Humane Tribunal, they are, and are to be
approved as conſonant to the Law. The Law is that Rule whereby they are to be
examined and approved, and rejected accordingly. For before the Tribunal of the
Lord, they are only approved and accepted as they are waſhed in the Bloud of
Chriſt, and have his Cleanneſs put upon them: That is, not in their active
conſonancy to the Law, but paſſively in the Grace of the Goſpel, which
is that incenſe which makes the prayers of the Saints to be accepted,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p>But the Law may alſo be conſidered formally and actively, to
wit, not only in the matter, but in the bond of it. What is that ſome may
ſay? I anſwer, it is that which formally binds to the performance of it.
Even that Covenant or Condition which lies in the Law, &amp; conſtrains to
the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98510:12"/> of it. Do this and live: Do not this and
be Accurſed. Here what is that which formally ties to the doing or not doing
of this? but life upon doing, and the curſe upon not doing? It is true, the
Authority of the Law-giver is the efficient cauſe of the Law, and of the
obligement of it; but the intrinſecal, formal and legal obligement
conſiſts in that relation which the thing commanded or forbidden hath
either to reward or puniſhment, without which there is no Law. In this
conſideration, I ſay it cannot be a rule unto the faithful: for the 2.
Exemption, which I mentioned before, is an acknowledged freedom from under the
Law in this conſideration. Thus much for a breif Explanation of my judgment
in this Matter.</p>
            <p>Now to that which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> Objected; <hi>That if the
Believer ſin, then is he under the Law.</hi> Hereunto I Anſwer, that a
Believer may be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Two wayes: 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Properly.</hi> Or,</item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Improperly.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Properly, as a Believer; <hi>i. e.</hi> As having a
perfect ſatisfaction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Law, as a juſtified perſon, as one
freed from ſin: <hi>For he that is justified, is free from ſin,</hi> Rom.
6.7. and ſtands without fault be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Throne and Tribunal of GOD, and
ſo as without Law. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you conſider this Believer Improperly here below
among men in his converſation, as a Worker, ſo there is Law for him as the
ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial and paſſive rule of his converſation, as I ſaid before, and
ſo there is tranſgreſſion by him; yea, as is ſaid, and proved before,
in every action he ſins.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>G. How can this ſtand with that which they
hold, That they which are Juſtified, are ſo Sanctified and purged, that
they are now for the preſent without ſpot or wrinkle.</hi> I Anſwer, very
well by the former Diſtinction: And further Sanctification may be taken in a
two-fold ſenſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For that Holineſs, which is Inherent, Active, and of
Works; which as it is in it ſelf Imperfect, ſo it is not able to preſent
us Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and Clean in the ſight of GOD, becauſe it ſelf hath need of a
perfecter and cleanſer. Or,</p>
            <p n="2">2. For that Holineſs, which is imputed paſſive, and of
Faith; in which ſenſe I ſhewed it to be taken, by certain Scriptures
cited by <hi>Ameſius;</hi> which Holineſs, in as much as it is perfect, in
it we alſo are preſented perfect, and without ſpot or wrinkle before God,
<hi>Col.</hi> 1.20. &amp; 2.22. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26,27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. In this, and the ſubſequent Sections to the
end of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, <pb n="15" facs="tcp:98510:12"/> Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> finds fault with
the Doctor, becauſe he denyes our peace to depend upon works of
Sanctification which we perform. This Mr. <hi>G.</hi> calls <hi>flinging
againſt Sanctification and Holineſs,</hi> but Wiſdom is juſtified of
all her Children. When <hi>Eſay</hi> called it <hi>menſtruous raggs,</hi>
Eſay 64.6. Chriſt, <hi>unprofitable ſervice;</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi>
eſteemed it <hi>dung.</hi> Will you call theſe <hi>flings at
Holineſs?</hi> No, they are only the attributing to them their true worth and
weight by the ballance of the Sanctuary. For ſeeing all our works have an
admixtion of ſinfulneſs, whereby they are truly ſinful works; and every
ſinful work, as the proper wages of it deſerves, eternal death, we may
thereby take a true eſtimate of their proper worth and efficiency. Miſtake
me not; This I mean, not as they are Good, and as they are Holy; but as they
are not ſo Good, and ſo Holy as they ought to be; and in regard they are
thus Imperfect, they are not able to ſpeak Peace unto us. Peace is fruit and
effect of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, <hi>Eſay</hi> 32. Therefore Chriſt is our
<hi>Melchiſedec,</hi> our King of Righteouſneſs; and afterwards, or
thereupon, our <hi>King of Salom;</hi> that is, <hi>King of Peace,</hi> Heb.
7.2. Therefore all our peace is attributed to Chriſt alone: He alone is our
Peace-maker, and in him alone is the full meſſage and manifeſtation of
our peace contained; and therefore God is ſaid to have <hi>come and preached
peace by Jeſus,</hi> Eph. 2.17. And as our peace is aſcribed unto Chriſt,
and the meſſage concerning it, ſo it is <hi>denyed</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our works:
Which that it may the better appear, we are to conſider our peace in a double
Notion; Either 
<list>
                  <item>1. As it is made with God: Or,</item>
                  <item>2. As it is manifeſted and ſealed unto our
Conſciences.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If we attribute it to our works in the firſt ſenſe, we do
manifeſtly put them in the place of Chriſt, and thereby rob him of the
dignity of his Prieſtly Office, whereby he <hi>is our Peace,</hi> Eph. 6.14.
<hi>Our propitiation with the Father,</hi> Rom. 3.25. Joh. 2.1,2. <hi>Our
reconciler unto God,</hi> Rom. 5.10. For all theſe are ſo peculiar unto
Chriſt, as the only Mediator between God and man; that whoſoever attributes
them unto any other perſon or thing, muſt of neceſſity attribute
thereunto the Mediatorſhip either in whole or in part. Peace in this
ſenſe is ordinarily acknowledged by Proteſtant. Writers not to depend on
Works. Notwithſtanding in ſome late ones there are ſome very dangerous
expreſſions tending ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly to the diſhonour of Chriſt,
attributing even the aboliſhing of the hotteſt wrath that can be in God
unto our performances: which, it were meet, they ſhould rather humbly, for
the honour of Chriſt, retract, than for the maintaining of their own
reputation, go about to ſalve and maintain; and that they who will not admit
of any expreſſion, which they conceive may derogate from their own Works
and Holineſs, ſhould <pb n="16" facs="tcp:98510:13"/> not dare to be ſo bold with the
peculiar honour and dignity of the Lord Chriſt, which he will not give unto
another, as to arrogate it to themſelves, and their own doings. Is this that
Humiliation and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſo much ſpoken of? I thought it had been the
utter denial of our ſelves, even the reſerving unto our ſelves nothing
but ſhame and confuſion and of faces; that we might with regard of any
thing in us lie naked and deſtitute, and hopeleſs and helpleſs before the
Mercy Seat of the Lord. Not a proud <hi>Luciferian</hi> advancing of our
Humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with ſuch terms and titles, that greater cannot poſſibly be
given to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, the King of Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This peace is conſidered, as <hi>manifeſted unto
us,</hi> and ſealed to our Conſciences, and in that regard alſo it doth
not depend upon works of Sanctification that we have or can do. Now this peace
is nothing but the ſtamp and impreſſion of the other upon our hearts: And
as it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed without works, ſo it is manifeſted without works, only
by Faith, which is a gift of God, whereby we look out of our ſelves for Peace
and help, that ſo (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>it might be by Grace, that the
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe might be ſure to all the Seed.</hi> Here the Apoſtle plainly
affirmeth, That the Promiſe, wherein is comprehended our peace with God, is
made ſure unto us only by Faith; which, as I ſaid, looks out of our
ſelves for its ground and object, and not by Works: For then the Apoſtle
plainly implies, that the Promiſe ſhould not have been ſure to all the
Seed. And therefore in <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. <hi>Ver.</hi> 1. upon our <hi>being
juſtified by Faith,</hi> he immediately infers, without the intervening of
the ſight of any Works, that <hi>we have peace with God.</hi> And that this
may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood only of the former peace, he ſhews it plainly in the
following words, by the effects of a manifeſted peace in the Conſcience,
<hi>and rejoyce in the hope of the glory of God.</hi> Neither is this a weak
unſetled peace, which muſt be ſtrengthned and under-propped by Works; But
it is a firm, and ſetled peace, even ſuch a one as bears up the Heart, even
to <hi>Rejoyce in Tribulation,</hi> ver. 3. So that only by this believing in
Chriſt, <hi>We rejoyce with joy unſpeakable,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. Yea, by
<hi>Believing, we are filled with all joy and peace,</hi> Rom. 15.13. Hereunto
<hi>Calvin</hi> giveth teſtimony, <hi>In Chriſt we have boldneſs and
acceſs with confidence, by the Faith of Him. This ſurely doth not befall
unto us by the gift of Regeneration, which as it is alwayes imperfect in this
fleſh, ſo it containeth in it ſelf manifold matter of doubting,</hi>
Calv. Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 13. Sect. 5. Here he not only challengeth our
aſſurance, and thereby our peace, wholly unto Faith; but alſo, he plainly
denies it unto the gift of Regeneration, which he affirms by the weakneſs and
imperfection of it to be rather the cauſe of doubting, than believing. And
therefore the truly Faithful have alwayes found it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the
ſearch for peace to go out of themſelves, to lay aſide their 
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98510:13"/> own Righteouſneſs as an hinderance rather than a
furtherance, as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, and to make mention of the Lords
Righteouſneſs onely, mentioned in the free Promiſes of his Grace without
works. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, that
Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am
chief,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. And this was a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe not onely for weak ones, not
yet well confirmed in works of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but even for an Apoſtle to lay
claim unto, and that upon no others terms or plea than that expreſſed, that
he was the <hi>chief of ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Contrariwiſe, that inherent works or holineſs have to do in
the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of peace and ſalvation of the ſoul, Mr. <hi>G.</hi>
endeavours to prove by two Scriptures.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>8. <hi>God will ſpeak peace to his Saints, but let them not turn
again to folly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> He might have done well to have ſhewed us how he
would draw his Inference from hence: It is, becauſe it ſaid that God will
ſpeak peace to his Saints, therefore their ſanctity or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs is the
ground, means or evidence of their peace and ſalvation? Then I Anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he might as well infer from the fore-mentioned
place, Chriſt came to ſave ſinners; therefore ſin is the ground, means,
and evidence of ſalvation, whereas it is onely a bare expreſſion of the
Object. And even ſo it is in this place.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is Obſervable, that which <hi>Junius</hi> and ſome
other of the Learned have obſerved, That
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (coming of
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>benignity, kindneſs,</hi>
or <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs</hi>) ought rather to be tranſlated in propriety his
Elect Ones, his Beloved Ones, thoſe to whom he is bountiful, and ſo he
tranſlates it in this place, <hi>erga eos quos benignitate
proſequitur;</hi> ſo that it ſignifies how God is affected towards them,
not how they are qualified towards Him. And then your Collection of the
dependance of peace upon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent holineſs cannot be deduced from hence. As
for the latter words, <hi>but let them not turn again unto follow:</hi> They
are not a commination or threatning, but a gracious dehortation grounded upon
the goodneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore revealed. And therefore <hi>Vau</hi> here is rather
<hi>illative</hi> than <hi>diſcretive,</hi> as it is moſt frequently; and
then the Text ſhould run thus, <hi>That ſeeing the Lord followeth them with
loving kindneſs, therefore let them not turn again unto folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other Text is that of <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 3.5. That <hi>not by
works of Righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his mercy he
ſaved us by the waſhing of Regeneration and Renewing of the Holy
Ghoſt:</hi> Whence he infers, that as Mercy is the moving Cauſe, ſo
Regeneration and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of the Holy Ghoſt, is a means of ſaving our
ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98510:14"/>The ambiguity here lies in the words
<hi>Regeneration and Renewing of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> I confeſs ſome
Learned Men do underſtand by the waſhing of Regeneration, (as
<hi>Calvin</hi> and others) an inherent Alteration in us, but I take it rather
for our Juſtification (as <hi>Melanct.</hi> on <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.) or
forgiveneſs of ſin. For as our Natural Generation makes us the Natural Sons
of our Natural Parents, ſo our New Birth or Regeneration, is that which
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes us the Sons of God. Now we are not made Sons by any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent
Qualifications, but by our Adoption, which is the immediate ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of our
Juſtification, neither of which are inherent in us, but are onely Relations
from God upon us. And in this place to me it is very evident: For otherwiſe
the Apoſtles words would include a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, as if he ſhould ſay,
Not of works of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighteouſneſs
that we have done, but by the waſhing of Regeneration, that is by inherent
Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, <hi>Viz</hi> By works of Righteouſneſs. For although in
theſe Qualifications, in the firſt infuſion we be conceived meerly
paſſive, and therefore in that reſpect they may not be called <hi>our
works</hi> of Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; yet as they can be ſaid to ſave, ſo
they muſt come forth into Acts and Workings, wherein we have ſome hand, and
ſo we ſhould be ſaid to be ſaved by works of Righteouſneſs that we
have done, if we be ſaid to be ſaved by them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the word <hi>Renewing,</hi> it is no new thing to
take it for that paſſive newneſs, whereby we are made new in the
Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, and in the perfection of that Reconciliation
which is brought upon us by him, whereby onely we are new in the ſight of GOD
which may well be ſaid to be of the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe it is reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
unto us onely by him, who takes of Chriſts, and ſhews it unto us,
<hi>Joh.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. Againſt thoſe that attribute ſalvation, or
the giving of peace to any thing beſides Chriſt, the Dr. applys that of
<hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.13. That therein, and ſo far they forſake the fountain of
Living Waters, and dig unto themſelves broken Ciſterns that will hold no
water.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>This,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>G. is not to the
matter. Why? Becauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Prophet
ſpeaks of turning from God unto</hi> Baal <hi>and ſuch Idols. But h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (the Dr.) <hi>hath applyed it
againſt thoſe things which God hath commanded and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended as
neceſſary; yea, and wrought in us by Chriſt himſelf,</hi> viz.
<hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sanctification and Sincerity.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, Firſt, That the diſtinction I formerly alledged
out of <hi>Chamier</hi> is to be obſerved, namely, That although thoſe
things, as they are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98510:14"/> commanded of God, or
wrought by Chriſt or his Spirit, be good; yet as they are ours, ſo they are
imperfect, weak and ſinful; ſo they are not commanded, to wit, to be done
imperfectly and ſinfully. And therefore I hope in that regard they may be
called <hi>Ciſterns,</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> Ciſterns, and Ciſterns of
our <hi>own digging.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Things may be conſidered, either in their own nature,
as they are the Ordinances of God, ſo they are good and commendable, or
elſe in their corrupt uſes, ſo they are by us made Ciſterns, and
bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Ciſterns. The Ordinances of Heaven, the Sun, the Moon, and the Stars,
they are in their nature very good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. But now if a man go about
to worſhip them, to expect help and deliverance from them, as the Old
<hi>Iſraelites</hi> and the Heathens did, therein I hope, and in that uſe
they may (notwithſtanding they be the Ordinances of God in other regard,) be
juſtly called broken Ciſterns that will hold no Water. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſo our works
and duties, as they are miſapplyed unto corrupt uſes, ſo they are broken
Ciſterns. All our Righteouſneſs are as menſtruous rags, <hi>Iſa.</hi>
64.6. Rags are but broken Cloaths, they will not cover us: If we go about to
cover our ſelves with them, we cover our ſelves with our own Confuſion,
as with a Cloak. For even ſhame and confuſion of face belongs unto us, and
that even in regard of our moſt Holy Performances, <hi>not becauſe they are
done,</hi> (this is the great miſtake of Mr. <hi>G.</hi> and others, who
thereby conceive he ſpeaks againſt the doing of goods works.) <hi>but onely
becauſe they are not done as they ought to be,</hi> that ſo we might in
true Chriſtian Humiliation and ſelf-denyal, take our right eſtimate of
our works, and of our ſelves, as conſidered in reference unto them, and
know that we are nothing. Accounting our very Righteouſneſs as all the
Faithful have done in their Generations, to be but as menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous rags: Not
onely <hi>Rags,</hi> as I ſaid, <hi>but</hi> menſtruous, filthy, unclean,
that when we go to cover our ſelves therewith, they are ſo far from making
us clean, that they defile. <hi>If,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, I make my hands never
ſo clean, my own Cloaths ſhall make me polluted, or abhorred.</hi> O how
far are they then from ſaving, from turning away wrath, from making
propitiation, things ordinarily attributed unto them by ſome; to which
uſes, without all queſtion they are but <hi>broken</hi> Ciſterns, and
will in a time of drought prove like the brooks in Summer, which <hi>Job</hi>
men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioneth. 
<q rend="inline">"But, O Lord, keep thy ſervant and thy people by
that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Living Water which is opened for ſin and for uncleanneſs,
wherein onely are the waters of comfort, by which thou as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sheepherd
leadeſt thy flocks, that they may draw water out of thoſe Wells of
Salvation, that bubble out unto Eternal Life, that ſo we may never thirſt
again, nor hanker after thoſe broken, empty, muddy Ciſterns, that will hold
no water."</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98510:15"/>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>G. how can he
ſay we forſake Chriſt, that by theſe duties ſeek ſalvation? Theſe
are not Ciſterns of our own digging, but of his appointing, and we uſe them
and humiliation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>onely in conſcience to his command, and not
as meritorious cauſes, but ſubordinate means of our ſalvation in the Name
of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, do you ſeek for ſalvation by your duties? Is this to
acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no, other Name, <hi>i. e.</hi> no other thing that can be named
under Heaven, by which we muſt be ſaved? Is this to confeſs that his own
Arm hath brought ſalvation, and that of the People there was none with him?
Have you ſo ſoon forgotten the Text you ſo lately cited, that not by
works of Righteouſneſs that we have done, but according to his own Mercy
hath he ſaved us? You ſay theſe are not <hi>Ciſterns of your own
digging, but of his appointing, and you uſe them as ſubordinate means of
ſalvation.</hi> You ſhould have done well to have ſhewed where he
appointed them to be ſubordinate means as cauſes of ſalvation; Chriſt
will not ſo be ſhuffled out of the Throne of his Glory: <hi>Salvation
belongeth unto the Lord;</hi> it is his peculiar. <hi>Beſides me there is no
Saviour:</hi> He hath not ordained any ſubordinate Saviours for the effecting
of ſalvation. If any thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him, be ſaid to ſave, it is but as
an effect, and by way of manifeſtation and declaration of his ſalvation;
not by way of effecting or producing it, either principally or ſubordinately;
either <hi>inchoatively,</hi> by giving any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſalvation, or by
way of <hi>compleating</hi> or perfecting ſalvation by way of efficiency.
There he is ſaid to ſave to the uttermoſt,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe that come unto God by
him; that is, thoſe that are brought unto him, thoſe whom the Father
draweth. <hi>Neither</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> Inſt. lib. 3. cap. 14.
Sect. 11.) <hi>doth</hi> Paul <hi>to the</hi> Epheſians <hi>ſay, that we
have the beginning only of ſalvation by Free Favour or Grace; but that by
Grace we are ſaved, not by Works, leſt any man ſhould boast.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Salvation in Scripture is taken two ways:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt;</hi> For the Firſt <hi>Conſtituting of us in the
ſtate of ſalvation.</hi> And in this Act, without queſtion, we are meerly
paſſive, we are dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, and we are meerly
paſſive in receiving Life. A dead man can be no way active, not
<hi>inſtrumentally and ſubordinately</hi> in giving Life unto
himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> It is taken for the full Complement and
Revelation of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Heaven, in the ſtate of Glory; and that alſo
we have freely from God for Chriſts ſake onely. <hi>How ſhall he not with
him alſo freely give us all things,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi>
8.32. Our works and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation here on earth, goes before the Revelation
of that Glory in Heaven, but they have no influx into it, as a <hi>motive or
moving Cauſe,</hi> 
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:98510:15"/> why God doth beſtow it upon us,
either in whole or in part: For <hi>Eternal Life is the Free Gift of God
through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> Neither as an <hi>efficient producing
Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the proper and native efficiency of the beſt
of our works, by reaſon of their imperfection, is the <hi>Curſe: Curſed
is he that conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not in all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they can have no other efficiency with God, but
that of a moving cauſe, which muſt needs be according to ſome Covenant or
Engagement; for otherwiſe, God cannot be Debtor to any man. Then the Covenant
muſt be that <hi>of works,</hi> which promiſeth nothing but to
<hi>perfection;</hi> and therefore, by that we can claim nothing; Or elſe by
<hi>the Covenant</hi> of grace, and there <hi>all the promiſes of God are
Yea, and Amen, in Chriſt</hi> onely. It is moſt abſurd, that works
perfect or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, ſhould be the conditions of a Covenant of Pure Grace:
And therefore, neither by nor <hi>for</hi> our works, can we be ſaid to have
either the beginning or complement of our ſalvation, but it is wholly to be
attributed unto the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who is the <hi>Author and
Finiſher, as of our faith, ſo of our Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>G.</hi> thinks the Dr. is in a contradiction, becauſe
<hi>heretofore he aſcribed all goodneſs wholly unto God,</hi> whereas
<hi>here he calls our duties a righteouſneſs of our own.</hi> In this
contradiction a caviller may find the Holy Scripture. When the Lord challengeth
to himſelf to Work all, both the will and the deed of his own good
pleaſure, yet the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> calls it our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,
when he ſaith all our righteouſneſs is as menſtruous raggs. It is
called <hi>ours</hi> becauſe we are agents in the action of it, though it be
Gods onely, in reference to the goodneſs of it, as is fully proved and
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained before.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>But what is this then</hi> (<hi>ſaith
Mr. G.</hi>) <hi>but to diſgrace Righteouſneſs and
Holineſs?</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Why, becauſe they are acknowledged to be what they are as they
come from us? why ſhould we not own the dung of our Solemnities, and the
uncleaneſs of our Holy things? That we may not think of any man or work above
that which is written, namely that there is <hi>none that doth good,</hi> no
not one; no not the great Apoſtle, who found no means to <hi>perform that
which is good,</hi> Rom. 7. That ſo God may have the full glory of his grace,
and man might be taught true Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, conſiſting in a real
and faithful renouncing of themſelves and their beſt doings, as unavailable
to commend them before God; not in a glorious magnifying, and ſetting of
great rates upon their Repentance, and other performances, which are direct
wayes to puff up; and how <pb n="22" facs="tcp:98510:16"/> they ſhould thus be wayes of
humiliation I know not: The Lord preſerve the Kingdom from the fruits of
ſuch Humiliation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. The Dr. had denyed that there is any ground of
Peace by Works; This Mr. <hi>G.</hi> acknowledgeth in regard of our peace with
God; <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>peace of Conſcience hath much dependance
upon Sanctification and Sincerity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us firſt take that which is granted, namely, that our peace
with God doth not depend upon our Works: And then let it be a dangerous
courſe, and an high intrenchment upon our Peace-maker, to think or go about
to make our peace with God by our Sanctification, or Sincerity or any of the
effects thereof. The Lord teach all his miniſters and people to acknowledge
this, not in word onely, but in deed and in practiſe.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"But, Secondly, Whereas he ſaith that <hi>peace
of conſcience hath much dependance upon Sanctification and Sincerity, out of
that</hi> (2 Cor. 1.12.) <hi>Our Rejoycing is this, the Teſtimony of our
conſcience, that in Simplicity and Godly Sincerity, not with fleſhly
wiſdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our converſation in the
world.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here we are to diſtinguiſh of a double Peace of conſcience
and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a double Rejoycing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> A peace of conſcience with God; whereby we are
aſſured that God is pacified towards us in the blood of his ſon. And this
is meant by that place cited by Mr. <hi>G. Rom.</hi> 5.1. That <hi>being
juſtified by faith we have peace with God,</hi> whereby it is not onely meant
a bare attonement with God, whereof we are not conſcious, but a manifeſted
peace, which is therefore ſaid to bring forth joy and rejoycing, which an
unknown peace could not do. And this peace of conſcience, <hi>de jure,</hi>
of right, ought to have no dependance upon Works: That is, though we are weak,
and as much as lyes in us, Covenant breakers; yet we ought to know, that the
Lord is faithful: He hath promiſed to do for his own ſake, and not
according to our Works, but according to his Grace. This Peace of Conſcience
therefore, ought, notwithſtanding all our fallings, to be acknowledged and
believed; although, I confeſs, that, <hi>de facto,</hi> and in practiſe,
the Children of God are not always able to conſider, and remember, and keep
their hearts up unto this Rock of peace and ſafety; eſpecially when the
Heaven above them ſeems to be black, and the Sea under them tempeſtuous,
with wave upon wave; ſo that, although by reaſon of their little Faith,
with <hi>Peter</hi> they begin as it were to ſink; yet ſtill at the length,
they find a gracious iſſue, and the hand of Chriſt ſtretched out to
ſave them, and the voice of Chriſt calling unto them, <hi>My Grace is
ſufficient for thee;</hi> yet notwithſtanding <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98510:16"/> they
ought with <hi>David</hi> to confeſs, that it is their own infirmity that
they did not cleave unto the faithfulneſs of the Promiſe, and remember the
years of the right hand of the Moſt High. This Peace of Conſcience
therefore with God, although <hi>de facto,</hi> as they ſay it be ſometimes
darkened by Works, yet <hi>de jure,</hi> it ought to have no dependance upon
them. And this is that Peace which the Dr. ſpeaks of, which cauſeth
rejoycing and glorifying in the Conſcience before God: But,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly;</hi> There is, another Teſtimony of the
Conſcience, or Peace thereof, and thereby rejoycing as the effect of it,
which hath relation unto men: And here, when we have done our duty towards men
in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity of heart, then have we peace of
Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards men. And this is the peaceful Teſtimony which the
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of here: For the former, that dependeth upon the
All-ſufficiency of the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, whereby God is perfectly
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled and fully at peace with us. But this dependeth upon our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere
and upright walking towards all men. The Apoſtle comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both, when he
ſaith, that he <hi>endeavoured always to have a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience towards
God and towards men:</hi> Towards God, in the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Son;
towards men, in the Righteouſneſs of a Chriſtian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, which
is matter of rejoycing amongſt men. But Mr. <hi>G.</hi> goes on: 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>And hence,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is St.</hi>
John's <hi>Phraſe: By this we know that we know him, if we keep his
Commandements,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.3. &amp; v. 29. <hi>Ye know that every one that
doth Righteouſneſs is born, of God.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning our eſtate towards God, and conſequently
our peace with God, We believe the fundamental Evidence to be the Teſtimony
of the ſpirit of God: <hi>The things of God knoweth no man, but the ſpirit
of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11. <hi>You have an unction from the Holy One, and ye
know all things.</hi> 1 Joh. 2.20. <hi>And hereby we know, that he abideth in
us by the ſpirit which he hath given us.</hi> The Evidence whereof we
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not to a Doctrinal Evidence or Revelation beſides the Word, but the
manifeſtation of that unto us, which is contained in the Word. It is, as I
may ſay, <hi>Revelatio revelans,</hi> diſtinct from the Word, but not
properly <hi>Revelatio revelata,</hi> as ſome I think have miſconceived; of
which revealed Evidence we are not now a ſpeaking, but onely of that
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing Evidence, whereby our hearts are effectually inclined to cloſe
with the Word, in which kind we believe the ſpirit of God, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be
the principal, but irreſiſtible and only effectual in his own Power. And
what light ſoever the other Evidences beſides this, have, they have it
together with their being from this ſpirit, as by the forecited Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
is apparent.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:98510:17"/>2. The next Evidence: We believe to be
Faith laying hold upon the free Promiſe of God's Grace towards us in
Chriſt: This the Apoſtle deſires to be the <hi>Evidence</hi> or
Conviction <hi>of things not ſeen; i. e.</hi> that, whereby we are convinced
of our intereſt in the inviſible Treaſures of the Goſpel, which
otherwiſe <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, neither have they entred
into the heart of man to conceive:</hi> And as the ſpirit of Chriſt, is by
Analogy, the ſoul of a Chriſtian; namely, That whereby all the Members are
knit together into one Body, <hi>(for he that is joyned to the Lord is one
ſpirit)</hi> ſo Faith is as it were the eye of this ſoul, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is
able to diſcern things not ſeen: And as the eye onely is that which ſees
bodily and earthly things; ſo faith onely is that which is held forth in the
Word, as the means to ſee ſpiritual things. This is held forth not onely in
<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. but alſo in all thoſe Examples which are there
mentioned by way of Induction to prove the ſame. And it is alſo a great
part of the meaning of thoſe places in <hi>Romans,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, in
which we are ſaid to be juſtified by faith onely, or by Faith without
Works: So the Reverend Prolocutor of the preſent Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, affirmeth,
when he ſaith, <hi>That the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is ſaid to be
imputed to us by Faith, becauſe it is not diſcerned to be imputed to us of
God, put by Faith,</hi> contra Armin. lib. 1. part 2. ſect. 25.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Works of ſanctification may be conceived to evidence.
1. To others. 2. To our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt to others:</hi> So are ordinarily to be conceived of,
when they are ſpoken of in the nature of Evidences. <hi>Shew me thy Faith by
thy Works,</hi> Jam. 2.18. <hi>By this ſhall all men know that ye are my
diſciples if ye love one another,</hi> Joh. 13.35. <hi>Let your light ſo
ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good Works, and glorifie your
Father, which is in Heaven, Mat.</hi> 5.16. In this way they are onely
Evidences unto the <hi>judgment of Charity,</hi> which judgment is ſufficient
for one man to have towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, reſerving the <hi>judgment of
certainty</hi> to an higher or more concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Tribunal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly to our ſelves:</hi> So they may be conſidered two
ways.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Barely as they are Works</hi> ſquared out according
to ſuch a rule, and to be judged of accordingly. So the Law of God being the
Rule, and thereby the Evidence of the goodneſs of Works, no Work in the Moral
Nature of a Work, can be judged good, which is not every way conſonant
thereunto; for it curſeth, and thereby, utterly diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Action,
and thereby the Actor, wherein there is the leaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonancy or
aberration therefrom. No Action therefore of Man having any other goodneſs,
but its conſonancy to this Rule, and no other Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thereof, but the
approbation of this Rule, can be judged to be <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98510:17"/> truly good,
ſo as to give evidence to the Conſcience, that things are well with it. For
the curſe which hangs over the imperfection of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is of far more
efficacy to ſcare the heart out of all its peace, than any pretended
goodneſs can be to pacifie it. For, as <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, <hi>A man
muſt not deceive himſelf, gathering, that therefore his work is not
altogether evil, becauſe it is imperfect, and that therefore that good which
is in it is nevertheleſs accepted of God,</hi> Inſtit. lib. 3. c. 2.
ſect. 4. Whoſoever therefore judgeth of himſelf by that inherent
goodneſs of his work, either he hath no peace, or deceives himſelf, as
<hi>Calvin</hi> here ſaith; and that which he hath, is falſe and
groundleſs. For the law, or the teſtimony there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of unto our works barely
conſidered, it is impoſſible it ſhould ſpeak peace, unleſs it can
firſt ſpeak or evidence Righteouſneſs. For peace is the fruit of
Righteouſneſs, not ſimply and abſtracted conſidered, but as it is
evidenced. Now the Apoſtle ſaith, That the <hi>Righteouſneſs of
God,</hi> wherein we are accepted, <hi>is manifeſted without the Law,</hi>
Rom. 3.21. And therefore, as the Papiſts and others deſtroy all peace with
God, and aſſurance of his favour, Doctrinally and in downright terms, ſo
they which have all their peace this way, deſtroy all peace and
aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Gods favour by conſequence and in effect.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are the effects of Faith, and in which it is
evidenced, ſo we confeſs, that not only in the pure and prime act of Faith,
there is an evidence, but alſo in all the acts of Chriſtian Love, even to
our ſelves. But how? Not by diſcovering an inherent legal good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in
them, (for that we rejected in the laſt) but only as true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith
is active and evidenced in them. For otherwiſe my Prayers, though they be
never ſo zealous; my Love, if it be never ſo vehement, if Faith be not
evidenced in them, can appear to be no more than the prayers and love of an
Unbeliever. But if Faith, to wit, the aſſurance of Gods favour be
manifeſted in them, then there is not only in them an evidence of Goodneſs
unto them, but alſo of Peace unto them, by this Faith which is manifeſted
in them. As for Example; I Love my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour? Why? What is it that ſets me
about this work, which kindles this Love in me? It is, becauſe I know God in
Chriſt hath loved me freely, and hath given his Son to me and for me. And
this known pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily only in the free promiſe of his Grace laid hold upon by
Faith. Notwithſtanding it is alſo exerciſed, and hath an influx into this
act of Love to my neighbour. For <hi>We Love him, becauſe he Loved us
firſt;</hi> That is, becauſe we know he loved us firſt. For unknown Love
hath no efficacy to produce a reflection of Love in him, upon whom it is
ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated. And as we love Him, ſo we love others for his ſake who hath
ſo loved us. So then, ſo far as our Love is truly Chriſtian; ſo far is
the Love of God to us manifeſted by Faith in it. And ſo in all the acts 
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98510:18"/> of true Chriſtian Love, there an is evidence of peace,
as in it Faith is acted, and the Grace of God to us therein taken notice of,
and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted. Now although ſome of thoſe places in <hi>John</hi> may
well be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted of the evidence of Works in reference to others: As the
latter of theſe here cited by Mr. <hi>G.</hi> if not the former; yet I
believe there are others that ſpeak of that evidence to our ſelves, which I
laſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained. In all or moſt of which places, I believe it is not
altogether unobſervable, that it is
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> herein, (not
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> hereby) which, as I conceive, is
more proper to the ſenſe expreſſed. Now to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place, 1
<hi>John</hi> 2.3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, herein or
hereby we know that we know him, if we keep his Commandements: To let paſs
that which ſome have obſerved, that
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is and may ſometimes be
tranſlated <hi>Agnovimus,</hi> we have acknowledged him ſo, that the words
ſhould then be tranſlated thus: Herein we know, that <hi>we have
acknowledged him, if we keep his Commandements:</hi> To let paſs this, I
ſay, or to leave it to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the judicious Reader; I
Anſwer, that <hi>John</hi> in <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 23. hath
explained himſelf what he means by his Commandements. <hi>This</hi> (ſaith
he) <hi>is his Commandement, That we ſhould believe in the Name of his Son
JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST, and love one another as he gave us Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</hi> Theſe
are his Commandements, not in a legal way, but as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the hearts of the
Faithful, by the finger of his Spirit, and as we are called forth to the
exerciſe of them, in the ſtrength of the ſame Spirit, by the glorious
manifeſtation of his grace in Jeſus Chriſt, unto us expreſſed, by
thoſe, and infinite ſuch Exhortations contained in the Word. By the
exerciſe of theſe two, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> there is then we
acknowledge an evidence of our good eſtate, and thereby peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In Faith, primarily by its own proper act going
out of a mans ſelf, and laying hold on JESUS CHRIST, for our ſufficient
Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Peace-maker. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In Love, as I ſaid, not by conſideration of
the inherent goodneſs of it, but in its ground, and as the influence of Faith
is in it, and upon it; for ſo only it is evidenced unto us, and conceived by
us to be a truly Chriſtian Act.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>G.</hi> addeth, <hi>We do not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>look
for peace of Conſcience from the ſubduing of our luſts, as the primary
cauſe, but as a ſure ſigne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant of the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer as before, that ſubduing of Luſts of it
ſelf, without the light of Faith ſhining, and giving evidence, that they
are expiated before God in the death of Chriſt, is no evidence at all; and
therefore no ſure ſign or concomitant, no more than that ſubduing of
Luſts which we read of in Heathens, in Jews, in Turks, and Papiſts in their
Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries at this day; theirs is without true Faith, and ſo is this. But
if you grant the aſſurance and evidence of faith in your ſubduing of
luſts, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:98510:18"/> then I grant there is an evidence of peace in it,
as that Faith ſhines forth in it, which giveth the light of the knowledge of
the appeaſed countenance of God towards us in the face of Jeſus Chriſt,
and no otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. In this Section Mr. <hi>G.</hi> as he hath done
divers times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, inſtead of diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roving what he had before him, makes an inference of his own or
ſome others ſlandrous coin, and that he layes to our charge, but he muſt
either own it himſelf, or elſe he muſt name the Author of it. It is, that
<hi>we ſlight Godly Sorrow which the Apoſtle ſo much commends,</hi> 2
Cor. 7.9,10,11. I profeſs that I am a ſtranger to any perſon or Author,
I mean, of thoſe that profeſs the Goſpel, that ſlight Godly Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. It
is an ungodly and unbelieving Sorrow which we ſpeak againſt; That Sorrow
which is ſtirred up upon the apprehenſion of Gods faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and conſtant
love towards us, and our weak and unanſwerable walking towards him; this
Sorrow, ſo far as it doth not intrench upon true faith, nor any way darken or
queſtion the ground of it, we have always approved; and we ſay, where true
faith is, it will always be as occaſion is offered. But when this is
degenerated into a Sorrow of unbelief, or into a <hi>Popiſh and dead
contrition</hi> (as <hi>Luther</hi> calls it) then we cannot allow of it: of
which degeneration this is a ſure ſign, when by it the appeaſed face of
God our Father is covered and kept out of ſight by it. <hi>All this ſorrow
and ſadneſs,</hi> ſaith <hi>Luther, is of the Devil, and it is a
ſacrifice very acceptable unto him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas the Dr. had asked, whether we could chuſe but fall foul
up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own Spirits, when we ſee the filthineſs and infirmity of our
wreſtling with ſins; <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Goree</hi>)
<hi>we cannot chuſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but fall foul upon our ſelves, and ſay with
the Apoſtle, O wretched men that we are, who ſhall deliver us from this
body of death,</hi> Rom. 7.24. <hi>And alſo with the publican, Lord be
merciful unto us Sinners,</hi> Luke 18.13. <hi>But now,</hi> ſaith he,
<hi>let us ask them, whether upon the ſight of their defects they fall thus
foul upon themſelves or no? I am afraid</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>they follow the
Phariſee rather than the Publican, boaſting ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than praying for pardon
of Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely if we ſhould do as Mr. <hi>Geree</hi> doth here in
effect, ſay we are humbler than you, we ſhould indeed play the Phariſees
and boaſters. But yet we may very well ſay that Mr. <hi>G.</hi> had no
ground for this ſentence upon us. We acknowledged the evil of all our
actions, and that (as he ought to have judged in chriſtian charity) in true
hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation and ſelf-denial, to be ſo great, that they deſerve the
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God even unto eternal death, acknowledging nothing in our 
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98510:19"/> ſelves as of our ſelves, but matter of ſhame and
everlaſting confuſion; which you were ſo far from conſenting unto, that
you call it a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracing of righteouſneſs and holineſs, <hi>Sect.</hi>
9. whereas in the ſame Sect. you affirmed of your duties that you ſeek
Salvation by them. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be nearer the Publican or the Phariſee, let
the godly reader judge.</p>
            <p>Yet if we add to the acknowledgement of what we are, in, and of
our ſelves, even in the beſt of our works, that is, <hi>wretched men:</hi>
I ſay, if we add that which follows in the Apoſtle, <hi>viz.</hi> that we
<hi>thank God through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> namely, that there is an
alſufficiency in him for us, though of our ſelves, even in our beſt
works, we be worſe than nothing: yet you ought not to call it following the
phariſee, or boaſting; or if you do, yet we ſhall alwayes deſire thus
to make our boaſt of the Lord, and to glory in his ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. The Dr. had ſaid, that Chriſt ſubdues
ſin in the faithful, as well as ſatisfies for ſin; But yet, ſaith he,
we are not to ſeek or receive our peace from this ſubduing of Sin, but from
Chriſt alone. Theſe two Mr. <hi>G.</hi> thinks <hi>croſs one
another,</hi> but yet he doth not ſhew wherein, and therefore I ſhall not
go to ſeek a knot in a bulruſh. Only I ſhall examine his reaſons
againſt the latter of theſe; the firſt is this.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>Let me tell them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that
if Chriſts power be ſeen as well in Sanctification, as in Juſtification,
what wrong can this be to Chriſt, to ſeek and ſettle peace in our
conſciences, as well by Sanctification as Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>To the matter of this, and what we hold in this Point, I have
an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered before. To the inference, I ſay there is no ſtrength in it,
that becauſe they are both effected by the ſame power, therefore the ſame
effects are to be attributed unto both. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> himſelf, I doubt not,
will grant my inference unſound, if I ſhould reaſon thus, Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication
is effected by the ſame power of Chriſt with Juſtification, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
Sanctification preſents juſt before God, as well as Juſtification. If he
allows not this argument, then he may ſee the face of his own in this
glaſs. As for our peace, it is neceſſary that we have a firm rock to
ſeek it from, that is able to ſpeak peace at all times, even in the
deepeſt plunges; which our Sanctification is not able to do: being feeble,
and dark, and weak at all times, eſpecially when it ſelf is que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned.
And therefore <hi>David</hi> ſaid, <hi>I will make mention of thy
righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs only.</hi> And our Saviour ſaith, <hi>in me ye ſhall
have peace.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we dare expect no peace from any one below
him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beſides,</hi> he demands, <hi>where we read in all God's
Word, that he was <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98510:19"/> ever angry with his People, for
ſeeking comfort in ſincere ſanctification and holineſs.</hi> I
Anſwer, That when the Apoſtle would ſhew the true po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Grounds,
where Conſolation is to be ſought, he fixeth them onely upon two things.
Firſt, the <hi>free promiſe</hi> of God without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect had unto, or
condition of works, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13,14,15,16,17,18. Surely, ſaith he,
in bleſſing I will bleſs thee, and in multiplying I will multiply thee.
And the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. That that ſame bleſſing of
<hi>Abraham</hi> comes on the faithful through faith freely not through works.
And the other thing that the Apoſtle mentions, is the <hi>Oath</hi> of God to
perform his promiſe, which Oath, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith, admits of no
repentance, or recalling back that which is ſworn unto. <hi>The Lord
ſwears</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and will not repent.</hi> And theſe two the
Apoſtle ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth to be ſufficient ground of conſolation, and that
is the end of God's propoſing them, <hi>to wit, That by two immutable things,
in which it is impoſſible that God ſhould lye, we might have ſtrong
conſolation, who have fled to the refuge, to lay hold upon the hope ſet
before us.</hi> Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt with all that he hath done, ſuffered,
and purchaſed for us, is the ſubſtance of this Promiſe, therefore it is
called, <hi>Conſolation in Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 2.1. who is the
<hi>conſolation of Iſrael,</hi> Therefore, till there be an inſufficiency
of conſolation in Chriſt, and in what he is unto us, we need not ſeek for
conſolation elſewhere in any other thing whatſoever. And in particular,
if we ſeek for it, in or by our own doings, we ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be
diſappointed. The conſolations of a Chriſtian are in the ground of them,
and therefore ought to be in the exerciſe of them, everlaſting
conſolation. But the truly experienced Chriſtian finds dayly, that when he
ſets himſelf before the glorious Tribunal of the Lord, all his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
becomes as the Morning Dew, and vaniſheth in a moment. And if it be not able
to ſtand by me there, what comfort can it be unto me, that thus leaves me in
my greateſt ſtraits and terrors? What's all my comfort, but to be found
there without ſpot, and blameleſs? That onely, that can ſtand me
inſtead there, is able to comfort: All other are miſerable Comforters, and
Phyſitians of no value. Conſider I pray thee, good Reader, that of
<hi>Calvin,</hi> worthy to be written in Gold; and I beſeech the Lord, thou
mayſt be ſo affected, as I was in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of it. 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Conſider thy Judge before whom thou
ſtandeſt, as he is in himſelf, not according to thine own imagination,
but ſuch an one as he is painted out to us in Scripture, with whoſe
brightneſs the ſtars are dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, with whoſe ſtrength the mountains
are melted, by whoſe anger the earth is ſhaken, by whoſe wiſdom the
prudent are caught in their own cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and by whoſe purity all things are
found to be defiled, whoſe righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs the very Angels are not able to
endure, who will not account the guilty inncocent, whoſe vengeance, when it
is once kindled, peirceth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the neither moſt Hell: Let him I ſay, ſit
in his Throne to examine</hi> 
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98510:20"/> 
                  <hi>the Actions of Men,</hi>
[that according to his ſentence of them, they may receive comfort] <hi>and
then who can ſtand ſecure before his Throne? Who can dwell with devouring
Fire? Who can abide with everlaſting Burning? He that walketh in
Righteouſneſs, and ſpeaketh the Truth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>let ſuch a man
come forth whoſoever he be: Nay verily, that Anſwer makes that we dare not
appear: For on the contrary, that terrible voice ſoundeth out, If thou Lord
ſhalt obſerve iniquities, Oh Lord, who ſhall abide?</hi>"</q> Inſtit.
lib. 3. c. 12. Sect. 1. It may be, ſome will Object, That <hi>Calvin</hi>
ſpeaks this of Juſtification, which I confeſs he doth; yet
not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſpeaks fully to the Point in hand: For whereas there
are but two Tribunals, at which the Conſcience of a man needs ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
and accordingly gathers Peace and Comfort, <hi>viz.</hi> The Tribunal of Man,
and the Tribunal of GOD: At Man's Tribunal, the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is at peace, and
comforted when it hath a Righteouſneſs as is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table among Men; and
here we grant Works of Sincerity and Love, their place: But at the Tribunal of
GOD, we ſay with <hi>Calvin,</hi> That <hi>before this terrible and
conſuming Fire, this ſtubble vaniſheth into nothing, it is able to yield
no peace, to give no comfort.</hi> Here there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but by being in
the hole of that ſure Rock Jeſus Chriſt the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, whilſt that
dreadful and unapproachable Preſence paſſeth by: This is the onely refuge
of ſafety, wherein exerciſed Conſciences per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that they may ſafely
breath. But if Men yet will needs be tam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering with comfort from their own
Works, and not be content with what may be had by that ſole ſure Rock of
Eternal Comfort, I ſhall leave them to meditate upon the terrible ſentence
of the Lord, which ſhall ſurely be performed in its ſeaſon,
<hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.11. <hi>Behold all ye that kindle a fire, that compaſs
your ſelves about with ſparks, walk in the light of your fire, and in the
ſparks that ye have kindled, this ſhall ye have of my hand, ye ſhall lye
down in ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"<hi>But,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>G. ſee how
good</hi> Hezekiah <hi>pleads with the Lord,</hi> Iſa. 38.3. <hi>Remember me
O Lord I beſeech thee, how I have walked before thee in truth, and with a
perfect heart, and have done that which is good in thy ſight. Hereupon he was
not rejected, but received a most gracious Anſwer,</hi> ver. 5. <hi>Go, ſay
to</hi> Hezekiah, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord, I have heard thy Prayer, I have
ſeen thy Tears, Behold I will add unto thy days fifteen years.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto I ſhall not Anſwer with <hi>Luther,</hi> that <hi>in
this Prayer,</hi> Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah <hi>manifeſteth ſome ſpice of that temper he
was in, when he ſhewed unto the Ambaſſadors of the King of</hi> Babel,
<hi>all his glorious Treaſure,</hi> although the Event and Anſwer, will not
ſhew the contrary. The lying of the Midwives of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in
<hi>Aegypt,</hi> had a proſperous Event, and a gracious Anſwer from the
Lord, who built them houſes; yet the Act muſt not therefore be concluded to
be approved of the Lord: And <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98510:20"/> indeed this Expreſſion is
very ſingular, and hardly to be found in the whole Scripture, in the mouth of
any of the Servants of God. Yet I conceive, that it ought rather to be taken
notice of, as agreeable to the Tenure of that Typical and Subſervient
Covenant, under which he was with the reſt of the Fathers of the Old
Teſtament, until the Death of Chriſt: In which Covenant they had outward
Bleſſings, among which, length of days was one, <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.2.
according to their upright walking with God in the performance of that
Covenant. The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is at large expreſſed in the 27, 28, 29 Chapters of
<hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> wherein all outward Bleſſings, even to the prolonging
of their days in that good Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> flowing unto them with all
ſtore and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of milk and honey; and wherein alſo all outward
Curſes were threatned againſt the Tranſgreſſors to the rooting of
them out, quite out of that good Land, and alſo out of the Land of the
Living, that they ſhould not prolong their days. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> having
therefore walked uprightly before the Lord in that Covenant, and reſtored the
Right Worſhip of the Lord, he prayed that the Lord would do unto him
according to his Promiſe in that Covenant; which manner of Plea ſeeing
grounded upon that peculiar Adminiſtration and Covenant, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to that
People, it ought not to be urged in the Times of the New Teſtament, where
that ſhadowiſh Adminiſtration even of the Moral Law is done away, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11. and aboliſhed, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. I have a little
explained my ſelf in this before; yet that, if poſſible, things may not
be miſtaken, I ſhall add a few words more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Although I ſay that this Covenant did properly
relate unto tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bleſſings and Curſes onely; yet far be it from me,
to think that the Faithful then had nothing elſe but temporal Bleſſings.
I confeſs, that by the Ancient Promiſe from the beginning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.
renewed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. They had all ſpiritual Bleſſings in Chriſt;
for ſo I before cited it out of the Apoſtle, that they were <hi>Heirs and
Lords of all;</hi> ſo that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly they were by Chriſt freely and
fully bleſſed, and juſtified, and ſaved.</p>
            <p>Yet <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſay, that according to this
ſubſervient Covenant and Adminiſtration, as the ſame Apoſtle ſaith,
they differed nothing at all from Servants: They were upon doing their Work,
and have their Wages; they were upon neglect of their Task, to be puniſhed or
thruſt out of doors. They had great Rewards of Glorious Proſperity upon
performance: They had ſore Afflictions and Calamities upon the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
thereof.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Queſtion may be, How this
ſubſervient Covenant could conſiſt with the promiſe of all
bleſſing in Chriſt? I Anſwer, very well, as the Apoſtle ſaith,
obſerving the right time; namely, that <pb n="32" facs="tcp:98510:21"/> the child at the
ſame time, whilſt he is a child, may be Lord of all; yet in all
adminiſtrations towards him, he may differ nothing at all from a Servant. If
indeed you take the Heir, when he is come to Age, and then make him differ
nothing from a Servant, then it is apparent you deſtroy his Heirſhip, and
alienate the Inheritance from him; But whilſt he is a Child, ſaith the
Apoſtle, he differeth nothing at all from a Servant, though at the ſame
time he be Lord of all: Even ſo was the difference between our Fathers before
Chriſt and Us, as the Apoſtle himſelf applyeth the Compariſon.</p>
            <p>But how can this be conceived, may ſome ſay? Could they be
Bleſſed and Accurſed at the ſame time? Could they be perfectly
Juſtified, and yet Sin charged upon them at the ſame time? This is the main
difficulty at which ſo many ſtumble: I ſhall therefore deſire the
Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader to take notice of what is ſaid, and I doubt not but the
Lord will afford Light for a ſolution hereof, according to the Analogy of
Faith, contained in the Holy Scriptures. I Anſwer,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Bleſſings and the Curſes of the
Old Teſtament were of ſuch a nature, as they had reference to this
ſubſervient Covenant, that the greateſt Bleſſings might have a real
Curſe under it; and the greateſt Curſe might have a real Bleſſing
under it. And ſo their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Juſtification might have a real charge of
Sin upon them, and their outward charging of Sin might veil a Spiritual real
and inviſible diſcharge and juſtification from ſin. This will be more
eaſily conceived, if we remember Two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this ſubſervient Covenant was carnal. It
conſiſted, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>in carnal Ordinances,</hi> Heb. 9.10.
ſerving to the <hi>purifying of the Fleſh,</hi> ver. 13. It conſiſted
in the <hi>rudiments of the World,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith
elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This ſubſervient Covenant was Typical. Things hapned
unto them, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Types, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 10. <hi>They were ſhaddows of good things to come, but the
ſubſtance was Chriſt,</hi> Heb. 10.1. And <hi>ſhaddows of Heavenly
things,</hi> Heb. 8.5. So then, that which in the judgement of the fleſh is a
Bleſſing, as all the proſperity of the Wicked is, may indeed and in truth
be a Curſe; <hi>I will Curſe their Bleſſings,</hi> Mal. 2.2. And alſo
that which is a Curſe in the judgment of the fleſh, being grievous unto it,
may indeed, and in the judgment of Faith, be a Bleſſing; and ſo are all
the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Faithful. And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Typical charging of ſin, will not prove a
real charge of ſin upon the ſame ſubject; as upon the ſcape-goat it did
only ſignifie the real charge of the ſin of the Iſrael of God was to be
upon him, <pb n="33" facs="tcp:98510:21"/> who was typified by that Scape-goat. So the
Typical charge of ſin upon many of Gods people, as <hi>David,</hi> and
others, did not ſignifie that he did really bear any dram of that Spiritual
curſe and puniſhment due to his ſin, but only that he in the fleſh bare
it as a Type of him that was to come.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It did ſignifie, that he that was to take away, and
bare ſin in his own body, was not yet come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It did ſhaddow out that when he did come, he ſhould
utterly take it away; ſo that none afterwards that belonged unto Chriſt,
ſhould bare it, either Typically, as the Sacrifices and Children of the Old
Teſtament, or Really, as Chriſt only hath done for all his.</p>
            <p>And this is the reaſon why there were ſacrifices of
Propitiation in the Old Teſtament, <hi>viz.</hi> Typically to ſhaddow out
the real attonement of Chriſt, which was to dome, <hi>Exod.</hi> 30.10,15,
&amp;c. <hi>Lev.</hi> 16. and very frequently elſewhere: Whereas in the New
Teſtament there are none, none at all either Typical or Real, ſince the
death of Chriſt. And therefore the Maſs is juſtly abhorred of all true
Chriſtians, as blaſphemous againſt the death of Chriſt, if it be
counted an attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or propitiation for ſin, either Typical or Real. If
the former, then it is a denial of Chriſt to be already come; For the Types
did all prefigure and confeſs that Chriſt was not come; If the latter, then
they muſt of neceſſity deny in whole, or in part, the ſufficiency of
that ſacrifice of propitiation that Chriſt offered once for all. And
therefore I do utterly diſlike the Expreſſions of ſome Miniſters, who
call our Faſting Dayes, <hi>Dayes of Attonement;</hi> whereby, if they mean,
that any thing that is done in them, can make an attonement or propitiation
either Typical or Real, then they bring an Idol of Jealouſie indeed into the
very Holy of Holies, and jump with the Papiſts in ſetting up an
abomination, to make deſolate, rather than to heal the Land, and bring a
bleſſing of peace upon it. However men may excuſe their meanings, I am
ſure ſome mens expreſſions are broad beyond all ſobriety. I am ſure
the Holy Ghoſt is very wary of giving any words of that kind, as Prieſts,
Altars, propitiations to any ordinances or actions of the New Teſtament,
beſides thoſe which are peculiar to the perſon of Chriſt alone.</p>
            <p>But if any underſtand by a day of Attonement, no more but a day
of Humble Addreſs unto the Throne of Grace (in confidence of that one
attonement offered once for all) for the effects of that one attonement and
propitiation to be manifeſted upon himſelf, and upon the Land: Then, as
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> once ſaid in another caſe, ſo I think I may as
juſtly ſay in this, <hi>Teneat mentem, ſed compeſcat linguam:</hi> Let
him retain this Meaning, but refrain that Expreſſion, being every way as
dangerous as that of <hi>Merit,</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and
<hi>Altars,</hi> or any ſuch like exploded phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <pb n="34" facs="tcp:98510:22"/>
But I have digreſſed ſufficiently; I muſt now return to Mr. <hi>G.</hi>
who goes on in this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover, when the Lord had condemned their Hypocritical
Holineſs and Services,</hi> Hay 1.11,12, &amp;c. <hi>Being much offended
with them, ſee what courſe he preſcribes them to make their peace with
him,</hi> ver. 16, 17, 18, 19. <hi>Waſh ye, make ye clean, take away the evil
of your doings from before mine eyes; ceaſe to do evil, learn to do well:
Then what follows? Come now, let us Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon together, ſaith the Lord,
though your ſins be as Scarlet, they ſhall be as White as Snow. If ye be
willing and Obedient, ye ſhall Eat the good of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> tells us, <hi>he doth but cite the very
words.</hi> Yes, he tells us alſo to what end he cites them, namely, as a
courſe preſcribed of God to make our peace with him. So that here it is
evident Mr. <hi>G.</hi> makes works not only evidences of our peace, but even
peace-makers; which office we dare not to attribute to any, but to the Lord
Jeſus, who hath made peace only by the blood of his Croſs, <hi>Col.</hi>
1.20. For as we acknowledge but one Mediator between God and man, ſo but one
peace-maker; For that was his office to mediate and effect a peace.
Reconciliation and peace-making is his own, his ſole Act. It is always in
Scripture ſpoken of in reference to a ſacrifice, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.18. And that a ſacrifice of propitiation
of appeaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which Chriſt only was able to offer. But the beſt of our
works are aſperſed with manifold defilements, they have need of an
atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to make peace for themſelves, ſo far are they from making peace
for others. But Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſeems to infer out of the place, that we our
ſelves, and that by our own doings muſt make our ſelves clean, muſt
take away the evil of our doings, from before the eyes of God; muſt ceaſe
to do evill, and learn to do well; and all this while we are the enemies of God
before our ſins be forgiven. So the Papiſt, and others before him, have
deſired to infer from the place. And this the Lord requires. How then ſhall
we anſwer to it? Sure our abilities are not the meaſure of Gods commands.
Such paſſages as theſe may well ſhew what is due unto God from man, not
what man is able to pay unto God. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> himſelf, if he would have
taken notice of it, hath collected for us out of Mr. <hi>Penible,</hi> a
ſatisfactory anſwer hereunto in his preface, <hi>Pag.</hi> 4. <hi>The
Law</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was added becauſe of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions; that
is, to convince man of ſin, that he might be put in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance what was his
duty of old, and what was his preſent infirmity in doing of it, and what was
Gods wrath againſt him for not doing it. That ſeeing how impoſſible it
was to attain unto life by this old way of the Law, first appointed in
Paradice, he might be humbled and driven to look after the New way, which God
had ſince that time laid forth more heedfully, attending the promiſe, and
ſeeking unto Chriſt, who is the end of the Law, <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98510:22"/> unto
every one that believes on him.</hi> And thus our peace is made, we are
waſhed, the evil of our doings is done away, out of the ſight of God. And
thus we ceaſe to be evil doers, and become truly well. doers, not in our own
actions, but in him who did all things well And ſo for his ſake, being
joynt heirs with him, we <hi>Eat</hi> and injoy the <hi>good of the Land</hi>
of the living, we have a ſure and unſhaken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, not only in Heaven,
but in earth alſo; ſo far as our fathers infinite wiſdom ſees them good
for us.</p>
            <p>Here, leſt we ſhould plead ſome difference between the
Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Mr. <hi>G.</hi> prevents us, ſaying, <hi>That the New
Teſtament differs not from the Old, in this particular.</hi> But mark the
Text he alledgeth, <hi>Chriſt was exalted to be a Prince, and a Saviour, to
give repentance unto Iſrael and remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Act. 5.31. And
is there no difference in this? Here Chriſt is plainly expreſſed, as a
giver of Repentance and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs: In that of <hi>Eſay</hi> it is barely
required of them. I confeſs, it was Chriſt that gave Repentance, and
Remiſſion of Sins, in all ages of the Church of God; yet this was not ſo
clearly manifeſted unto the people of the Old Teſtament, as it is to
thoſe of the New. The Old Teſtament is more frequent in Requiring of
Righteouſneſs (ſave only in thoſe places where it ſpeaks
Prophetically of the New) than in manifeſting the free gift of
Righteouſneſs. In the Old Teſtament it was, but <hi>my Salvation is near
to come, and my Righteouſneſs to be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed,</hi> Iſa. 56.1. But in the
New Teſtament, <hi>the Righteouſneſs of God is already Revealed in the
Goſpel,</hi> Rom. 1.17. The difference, ſo far as it concerns the preſent
particular, is moſt remarkable in the Apoſtles citing, and inverting that
place of <hi>Iſay</hi> 59.20. <hi>The Redeemer ſhall come to Sion, and unto
them that turn from tranſgreſſion in Jacob;</hi> which the Apoſtle
citing, doth wonderfully invert after this manner; <hi>The deliverer ſhall
come out of Sion, and ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from Jacob.</hi> In that
of the Prophet, <hi>turning from iniquity,</hi> ſeems to be pre-required to
the comming of the Meſſias: But by the Apoſtle, it is plainly reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to be the effect of his comming: <hi>He ſhall turn away ungodlineſs from
Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, from the fore-cited place, and that in <hi>Luke</hi>
24.47. wherein Chriſt chargeth his Apoſtles to Preach Repentance, and
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins among all nations, Mr. <hi>G.</hi> infers, <hi>mark
firſt Repentance, and then Remiſſion of Sins. This</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>is Chriſts Order.</hi> What? that Repentance ſhould go before
Remiſſion of Sins; Surely ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, can be no better, than the
Repentance of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> in it ſelf; for I ſpeak not
of the Event. For what can the Act of an enemy unto God be accounted to be, but
fruits of enmity? The Proteſtants uſe to ſay with Chriſt, that,
<hi>firſt the tree muſt be made good by <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98510:23"/>
juſtification.</hi> Wherein is contained forgiveneſs of Sins <hi>before the
fruit can be good,</hi> before we can do any thing acceptable unto God. But
repentance, you will ſay, is mentioned firſt. To this I Anſwer with
<hi>Calvin,</hi> that <hi>whileſt men ſtick in the order of letters and
ſyllables, they do not mark the coherence of the Senſe,</hi> Inſt. lib.
3. Cap. 3. Sect. 2. For as he ſaith there, <hi>it is impoſſible that a
man ſhould ſeriouſly repent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he know himſelf to be Gods. But
none is truly perſwaded that he is Gods, but he who first hath apprehended
his grace;</hi> ſee <hi>Calvin</hi> (ibid.) fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there where he
ſolidly proves, that faith, or the aſſurance of the forgiveneſs of
ſins, doth precede, and bring forth all true repentance, which is the general
judgment of all Orthdoox Proteſtants. For my own part, I conceive, that it is
ſo frequently ſet before faith, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, not becauſe
it ſelf doth either in order of time or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture precede them; but becauſe
it relates properly unto that eſtate of unregeneracy, which both in order of
time, and nature, goes before converſion, and regeneration, whereunto faith
doth properly refer. But ſtill this muſt be firmly holden, That <hi>we love
him becauſe he loved us firſt,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.19. That <hi>becauſe many
ſins are forgiven us, therefore we love much,</hi> Luk. 7.47. That <hi>with
the Lord is propitiation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall he be feared,</hi> Pſal.
130.4.</p>
            <p>And now I deſire the Chriſtian Reader, to ſet himſelf, as
<hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith, not <hi>in umbraculo,</hi> at eaſe, full of the
works of his own hand, and of the applauſe of men, but ſeriouſly
ſenſible of the dreadfull ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of the Lord, that not he that commendeth
himſelf is approved, but he whom the Lord commendeth; And then let him ſay,
whether he will lean unto ſuch a peace as his works will be able to make, or
that only which the great Peace-maker hath made by the Blood of his Croſs,
<hi>Col.</hi> 1.20.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:98510:23"/>
            <head>THE DEFENCE OF THE Second Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 1, 2. THE Subſtance of the Firſt Section Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> would gladly ſeem to grant, namely, That <hi>God doth no longer
ſtand of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended with a Believer, though after he be a Believer, he doth ſin
often:</hi> Yet in the end he will not let it paſs for current without ſome
Qualification, which he explains more fully in the ſecond Section, in his
Anſwer to that of <hi>Eſa.</hi> 27.4. <hi>Anger is not in me.</hi> Here
ſaith he, the word <hi>Chama</hi> (he or his Printer ſhould have ſaid
<hi>Chemah</hi>) <hi>in the Original is rendered</hi> Excandeſcentia,
<hi>Burning, or fiery Wrath, which the laſt Tranſlation calls Fury very
fitly, which teacheth what kind of Anger is not in God,</hi> to wit,
<hi>conſuming wrath, or anger of an Enemy to deſtroy; yet may God be ſaid
to have a Fatherly Anger, which may ſtand with Love: For the Scripture
ſpeaks of God after the manner of men.</hi> Hence, Rev. 3.19. <hi>As many as
I love, I rebuke and chaſten.</hi> Rebukes and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements are effects
of Anger, as well as of Love.</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt of all Explain what we hold in this particular,
and then proceed to Anſwer what Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath here Objected.</p>
            <p>Anger may be attributed unto God Two Wayes: Either, 
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>In the Affection of it.</hi> Or,</item>
                  <item>II. <hi>In the Effects of it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt in the <hi>Affection</hi> of it, altho' in propriety of
ſpeech, there be no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection congruent to our humane conceiving, and
anſwerable to the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and paſſions of men. For as God is not like
man in Repenting, <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.19. So in no other paſſion, ſo in no
other thing, conceiveable by an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man underſtanding. Thus <hi>He dwells in
the Light, that no Man can approach unto,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.16. Yet hereunto may be
referr'd the dreadful punitive Juſtice <pb n="38" facs="tcp:98510:24"/> of God, whereby
he pays unto ſin, and to the ſinner, his juſt Wages. For, becauſe it is
expreſſed in the Scripture by that which is an affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in man, and
becauſe the effects of it are in ſome way proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thoſe of
Anger in Man; therefore may we, with the Learned, call it <hi>Anger in the
Affection:</hi> Yet not conceiving of it in the notion of an humane
paſſion, but of <hi>puniſhing Justice.</hi> So <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. The
higher powers are ſaid to be the Miniſters of God,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Revenger in Wath, or to
Execute Wrath. What! To execute his own or other mens paſſion upon the
Offender? No ſuch matter; but a Revenger, by puniſhing Juſtice, or to
execute Juſtice upon him that doth Evil. This word <hi>Anger,</hi> or Wrath,
I confeſs, may be drawn up higher to that dreadfull Sentence paſſed
within God himſelf from all eternity upon the veſſels of Wrath; but this
ſignification is leſs pertinent to our preſent matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is Anger in the <hi>Effects</hi> of it;
which as it is origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally and radically upon all the ſons of <hi>Adam,</hi>
both Elect and Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, ſeeing all are originally under the Law, and by
breaking of it, their mouths are for ever ſtopped, to wit, from pleading
innocency by that Covenant, and all the world is become (<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.19.) ſubject to the Judgment of
God, and Children of Wrath, even as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12. So it is by
derivation from the Elect, as their ſin is tranſlated, upon their ſurety.
For there is no Anger in the Effects, but in reference to Sin, as the cauſe.
Whereſoever there is a rupture in the Houſe, there the ſtorm drives in:
So whilſt the Elect ſtand as Sinners, they ſtand liable to Judgment. I do
not ſay there was ever an actual or poſitive Execution of the VENGEANCE of
GOD, due for ſin, upon the Elect: For in that regard, they have obtained not
only a Reprieve, but a Diſcharge: But as their ſin was by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
derived upon Chriſt, ſo puniſhing Juſtice, Anger or Wrath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued
him; and from him received a full Satisfaction for whatſoever the Elect had
committed, and ſo in him ceaſed, in reference unto them.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing Imputation of ſin may be conſidered two wayes,
ſo alſo may the Anger, Wrath or Execution of Juſtice likewiſe be
conſidered either in the <hi>Type,</hi> or <hi>Antitype.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt</hi> in the <hi>Type;</hi> thus all the people of God
in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did more or leſs in a typical way bare iniquity, not
only in their ſacrifices, but alſo in their own perſons, yet ſo as
nothing of what the <hi>Antitype</hi> did, be darkned or impaired. Their
Sacrifices uſually, and their Works ſometimes, are ſaid to expiate or
appeaſe Wrath or Anger (2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.12.) which is all one. What, did
they herein any of Chriſts work of Satisfaction? No, they did only pre-figure
it; and according to the nature of their Covenant, as <hi>Types</hi> bare, and
as <hi>Types</hi> 
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98510:24"/> take away the imputation of Sin,
according to that carnal adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation then in being. For otherwiſe, if
a real taking away of ſin by theſe ſhould be aſſerted, then the
Apoſtles reaſon would not ſtand ſtrong in force; that it is
<hi>impoſſible that the Blood of Bulls or Goats ſhould take away
ſin,</hi> Heb. 10.4. (yet the ſame Apoſtle affirmeth, that they
<hi>Sanctified to the purifying of the fleſh,</hi> Heb. 9.13.) ſo alſo we
may, by the ſame reaſon, ſay, that it is impoſſible that the
imperfect and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful works of man ſhould take away ſin. Yet might they
in themſelves, by vertue of their ſubſervient covenant, ſanctifie to an
outward purify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fleſh, and in their Typical relation ſhaddow out
that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and everlaſting Expiation which was to come by the Death of
CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Now whereas it might be Objected, That <hi>Moſes</hi> by Prayer,
is ſaid to ſtand in the breach, to turn away his wrath, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
106.23. That <hi>Phineas,</hi> by executing judgment, ſtaid the plague: That
<hi>Noah, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Job, ſhould deliver their own Lives by their
Righteouſneſs,</hi> Ezek. 14.14. with infinite other ſuch Examples in the
Old Teſtament, which have theſe, with ſuch like effects attributed unto
them, without any expreſs mention of their <hi>Typical</hi> nature or
reference unto their <hi>Antitype</hi> Chriſt; I Anſwer, that herein
conſiſteth a great part of <hi>the Veil of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi> that
it did but very darkly point out to the Meſſias. So that Expiations and
Attonements are to a carnal eye attributed to the very Ceremony, there being
ſeldom or never, with the <hi>Type,</hi> any expreſs mention of the
<hi>Antitype,</hi> whereby the more carnal Jews terminated their thoughts in
the ceremony or action done. But the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath clearly revealed,
that the whole <hi>Paedagogy</hi> was but a ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow under which the people
of God of Old were ſhut up <hi>unto the Faith that ſhould afterward be
revealed,</hi> Gal. 3.23. And that fundamental argument of the Alſufficiency
of the death and ſatisfaction of Chriſt ſo fully proſecuted by the
Apoſtle in the 7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>Chapters</hi> of the Epiſtle to the
<hi>Hebrews,</hi> puts the matter beyond all Controverſie. That the Anger or
Wrath of GOD could only be born <hi>Typically</hi> by the Children of the Old
Teſtament, ſeeing it could onely be born really by the Son of God.</p>
            <p>But now <hi>Secondly,</hi> As imputation of ſin, and thereby
anger and wrath, or execution of juſtice, are conſidered in the
<hi>Antitype;</hi> ſo it is apparent, that Chriſt did both really bare and
take away all Anger due to the Elect for their ſins, as well of thoſe that
were before his time, as of thoſe that came after.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He <hi>Bare</hi> all Anger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe he bare all ſin, the cauſe or
ground of this Anger, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe he bare all Puniſhments due to
ſin: He was <hi>bruiſed <pb n="40" facs="tcp:98510:25"/> for our Tranſgreſſions:
He ſuffered the Juſt, for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It appears by the real effects in his ſweating
great drops of blood, when no bodily Torment was upon him, which is more than
ever befel any man upon earth, by the moſt extream torture, but moſt
eminently in that terrible hideous Out-cry, wrung from him by the
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceivable weight of that wrath that lay upon him, <hi>My God, my God, Why
hast thou forſaken me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He <hi>took away</hi> all Anger.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is ſaid to be the <hi>Chaſtiſement of our
Peace</hi> which was upon him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5. He is the
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>placamentum; the
appeaſement of our ſin,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.1,2. By him we have received
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the attonement or
reconciliation. So that now to thoſe that are in him, there is no Anger, but
everlaſting well-pleaſedneſs, and perfect favour eſtabliſhed by a
Covenant of Salt, like that of <hi>Noah</hi>'s, without condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>As I
have ſworn that the Waters of</hi> Noah <hi>ſhall no more go over the
earth; ſo have I ſworn, that I will not be angry with thee,</hi> Iſa.
54.9. And that <hi>our ſins and iniquities he will remember no more,</hi>
Heb. 8.12.</p>
            <p>Now to what Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath Objected. <hi>Firſt,</hi> For
his Criticiſm, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>ſignifieth conſuming wrath, and the anger of an Enemy to
deſtroy:</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That his Obſervation will not hold, for it is
alſo uſed concerning the Anger of a Father, or otherwiſe a Friend among
men. And <hi>David</hi> m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kes it
Synonimous with <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which is moſt
uſually rendered Anger, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 6.1. <hi>Rebuke me not</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in thine anger,</hi>
whereunto is added, after the uſual exegetical manner of the Pſalmiſts
and Prophets, <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chaſten me</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in thy hot
diſpleaſure,</hi> where the latter Phraſe is of the ſame
ſignification with the former. And <hi>David</hi> deprecates both alike, ſo
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.7. where if there be any difference, the greater mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<hi>viz. Conſumption</hi> is attributed to
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the latter, <hi>viz.
Trouble,</hi> to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Both are
promiſcuoſly ſpoken of the Anger of a Friend, and that of an Enemy. It
may be you will ſay, that in this place is meant of the Anger of an Enemy. I
Anſwer, That in God (excepting that Typical Expreſſion of Anger, whereof
I ſpake before) there is no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger at all in God towards a reconciled People,
ſuch a one as he ſpeaks of in the immediately foregoing words, <hi>[God
hath no little Anger]:</hi> If his Anger be kindled but a little, it is well
with them that are out of the reach of it. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that
put their truſt in him: For who may ſtand in thy ſight when once thou art
angry,</hi> Pſal. 76.7. Chriſt hath ſatisfied for the whole Anger, little
and great, which was due to our ſins. Yea, ſay they, but the undergoing of
this, is not to make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: But Chriſt did not his Work by Words.
Neither is it enough to acknowledge his ſatisfaction in Words onely. Was his
ſatisfaction a full Appeaſement? Did it fully anſwer the whole demand of
God's Juſtice, for all the ſins of thoſe that are his, to the uttermoſt
farthing? <pb n="41" facs="tcp:98510:25"/> If not, then the acknowledgment of
ſatisfaction is but verbal, it is the full payment that makes ſatisfaction
nothing leſs: If a man owe an 100<hi>l.</hi> and pay but 99, he hath not made
ſatisfaction. He cannot ſay as Chriſt did, <hi>conſummatum eſt,</hi>
it is finiſhed. But ſay they, <hi>it it but a fatherly anger and
diſpleaſure.</hi> I Anſwer, That is in ſome reſpect the greateſt
and heavieſt Anger that can be. An ingenuous Child had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have all the
World angry with him than his Father. I am ſure the True believing Child of
God had. But if a Father have received a full ſatisfaction for the fault of
his Son, will he yet be diſpleaſed and retain his Anger? Surely none can
juſtifie that in an Enemy, much leſs in a Father: How then can it be in
ſuch a gracious Father as we have, who is an infinite everlaſting Ocean of
Love, Compaſſion, and Well-pleaſedneſs unto his Children. Yea, but
ſay they further, <hi>This expreſſion of Anger and Correction for ſin
is from his Fatherly Love.</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, That who ſo is compelled to
undergo Anger, (though it be but a mans) for that fault, for which a full
ſatisfaction hath been exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, even to the uttermoſt, will not eaſily
be perſwaded, that that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is out of, or agreeable to love, but rather
out of extreamity of rigor. It is true indeed, that all the afflictions of Gods
Children (or Chaſtiſements and Corrections, for ſo they are called in
regard of the diſtaſtefulneſs to the fleſh, and in regard of ſome
effects <hi>per accidens,</hi> which they have, bearing ſome Analogy to the
effects of Parents cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſing their Children): I ſay, all the
Afflictions of Gods Children are from his Fatherly tendereſt Love. The Lord
never manifeſts himſelf more ſenſibly unto their hearts, than in the
heavieſt of their Afflictions. He takes away earthly comforts out of their
ſight, that he may ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them with Heavenly. Inſomuch, that
hereupon the Martyrs have in the midſt of the flames, been as it were in Beds
of Roſes, and triumphed as more than Conquerors, through him that loved them,
which they could not have done in the ſence, though but of a Fathers Anger,
and in the juſt deſert of their ſins, if they had ſuffered from the
hand of God as evil-doers. And therefore, that Rebukes and Chaſtiſements
are always effects of Anger as well as Love, and namely, that they are ſuch
towards Gods Reconciled Ones, needed Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s Proof, not his bare
Affirmation.</p>
            <p>The Godly Martyrs, and Firſt Reſtorers of Religion in this and
other Nations, have born witneſs to this Truth. <hi>Patrick Hamilton,</hi>
that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Witneſs of Gods Truth in <hi>Scotland,</hi> makes the Voice of
the Law indeed, to be, <hi>The Father of Heaven is angry with thee:</hi>
Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he makes the Voice of the Goſpel to give a ſatisfying Anſwer,
<hi>Chriſt hath pacified him toward me.</hi> In his places Tranſlated by
<hi>Frith.</hi> So <hi>Luther,</hi> in <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15. 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Let us learn,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>even in
great and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Terrors, when our Conſcience feeleth nothing but ſin,
and judgeth that <pb n="42" facs="tcp:98510:26"/> God is angry with us, and that Chriſt
hath turned his face from us, not to follow the ſenſe and feeling of our
own hearts, but to ſtick to the Word of God, which ſaith, That God is not
angry.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Calvin,</hi> (Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 19. Sect. 6.) 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Although the Faithful do not feel ſin to be
extinguiſhed, nor Righteouſneſs altogether to live in them, yet there is
no reaſon, why they ſhould fear, or be caſt down, as if ſtill they had
God offended with them, for the remainders of ſin:</hi>"</q> And
elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Judicio caſtigationis non ita ſaevit Deus
ut iraſcatur,</hi>"</q> Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 4. Sect. 31. <hi>God is never
ſo much as angry in chaſtiſing his People;</hi> and in <hi>Sect.</hi> 32.
He anſwereth the Objections to the contrary.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.9. 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>We ought to determine with our ſelves, that
ſeeing the Anger of God is ended and taken away, that nothing is ſent upon
us by Him, but with a Fatherly and friendly mind; otherwiſe Afflictions and
Adverſities might in their own nature make us afraid, and perſwade us that
God is angry with us, which can no way poſſibly be, ſeeing reconciliation
is made by the death of Chriſt.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. To prove the full deliverance of the Faithful
from Wrath, the Dr. cites that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.11. <hi>He ſhall ſee
of the travel of his ſoul, and ſhall be ſatisfied.</hi> Here, although
Mr. <hi>G.</hi> I conceive, grants the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet, <hi>This Proof</hi> (he
ſaith) <hi>is meerly miſtaken: For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is all ſpoken
of Chriſt himſelf, who ſhall ſee of the travail of his own ſoul and
be ſatisfied; that is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the fruit of the travail of his
ſoul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereunto I Anſwer, That in all ſafe ways of expounding
Scripture, Two Things ought principally to be taken notice of, 1. The Analogy
of Faith. 2. The Circumſtances of the Text. Let us lay theſe Two to the
preſent Text.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Analogy of Scripture holds forth every where, that
Chriſt came not to make ſatisfaction to himſelf as Mediator, but to his
Father, who as the Learned ſpeak <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtands for the whole Trinity. Take his own Teſtimony; <hi>I
came not to do my own will, but the will of him that ſent me,</hi> Joh. 5.30.
When he offered himſelf a Sacrifice of propitiation, or ſatisfaction (as
Mr. <hi>Tindal</hi> tranſlates it) to whom was his Sacrifice preſented,
that it might propitiate and ſatisfy? The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>He offered
himſelf without ſpot to God,</hi> Heb. 9.14. not to himſelf: For although
he be indeed God, yet in this office he is conſidered as Mediator, and as the
perſon offering and Mediating; and God is conſidered as to whom the
Mediation is made, and the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offered. <hi>There is one God,</hi>
(there is the perſon Mediated) <hi>and one Mediator between God, and man, the
Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> There is the perſon Mediating; together with the
perſon, in whoſe behalf the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation is made. Chriſt therefore came not
to ſatisfy himſelf; and therefore it is not probable, nor conſonant to
the Analogy of faith, that here it ſhould be meant of the ſatisfaction of
himſelf.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98510:26"/>2. Conſider, will not the
circumſtances of the Text it ſelf yield as much? In the words immediately
before, he ſaith, That <hi>the pleaſure of the Lord ſhall proſper in
his hand.</hi> How ſhall the pleaſure of the Lord proſper in his hand?
Mark here firſt, that he is here ſpeaking of the pleaſure of the Lord,
not of the pleaſure of Chriſt. But how proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pereth the pleaſure of the
Lord in his hands? How, but (as the next words expreſs) by being ſatisfied
with the Travail of the Soul of his Son? That which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> objecteth,
That the words are, he ſhall ſee of the Travail of his Soul, as pointing to
the effect of Chriſts ſufferings, not to the ſufferings themſelves,
doth nothing infring what I have ſaid: For ſuppoſing that
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here doth ſignifie [of] or
proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from, whereunto for the preſent I do not remember a parallel; yet
ſuppoſing it doth denote the effect, what is the proper, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
effect of the Travail of the Soul of Chriſt, but <hi>ſatisfaction
active,</hi> as it is in the ſatisfier Chriſt, which immediatly produceth
<hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction paſſive,</hi> as it is in God the party ſatisfied.
That other effects are afterwards mentioned, they ought not to exclude that
which is Primarily, and expreſly ſet down, to wit, ſatisfaction; which is
a point of faith, which ought not to be darkened, upon ſuch ſlight or weak
ground as Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath here brought.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> would gladly bring in the Dr.
as finding fault with the cloudineſs of Proteſtant Divines, whereas he
mentioneth none, either in general or particular. And as he was a modeſt man,
far from the bitterneſs and invectives of many, that have ſpoken againſt
him both in preſs and pulpit; ſo did he never in his Sermons, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any
profeſſed oppoſition to any one, much leſs to all Proteſtant Learned
men. And for my own part, I dare undertake by the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of
Chriſt, to maintain that there is no matter of moment in all his Sermons,
which the beſt, and moſt Orthodox Proteſtant Divines that are extant,
have not aſſerted before, for which the odious impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of
<hi>Antinomianiſm</hi> was never caſt upon them. And this I hope, I ſhall
partly manifeſt to the indifferent Reader in this preſent anſwer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. To prove, that Chriſt alone underwent the
wrath of God for us, the Dr. cites that of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 63.3. <hi>He hath
trodden the wine-preſs alone.</hi> And in this, and his other proves Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> acknowledgeth, <hi>he hath trod in the ſteps of the Proteſtant
Writers.</hi> So then he is not altogether ſo oppoſite to them, as Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> would bear us in hand. But, ſaith he, <hi>in this place both he
and they were mistaken, which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is not meant of Chriſts
ſufferings for Sin.</hi> His Reaſons are two:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Becauſe Chriſt is ſaid to be an agent in
treading the wine-preſs, both here, and</hi> Rev. 19.13. <hi>Whereas in his
ſufferings he was paſſive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:98510:27"/>2. <hi>Becauſe in his ſufferings,
and ſatisfaction, he looked for none to help; but here it is ſaid, he
looked for ſome to help.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the 2. I anſwer, that metaphorical ſpeeches, are not to be
ſtretched beyond the intention of the Holy Ghoſt. In propriety of ſpeech,
Chriſt could not look for help from man in any kind, and miſs of his
expectation, for he knew what was in man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.25. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
neither could he wonder, which is the effect of Ignorance. What then may be the
Scope of the Holy Ghoſt? Surely to beat down the pride of man, who is alwayes
arrogating ſomthing to himſelf, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the matter of Salvation.
But ſaith the Prophet, when the work was a doing, when the wine-preſs was a
treading, then none would, none durſt appear. The Son of God might have
looked long, but he ſhould have found no help in them in any kind,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 146.3. And he might wonder as it were at the confidence of
man, in his great promiſes what he will do, and at his challenging what he
can and doth do; but the iſſue will be, that it will ſurely fall in the
Suds, if the Lord Jeſus bring not Salvation by his own Arm. This
expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, I am ſure is conſonant to the Analogy of faith, whereas Mr.
<hi>G</hi>'s. attributing in a proper ſence unto Chriſt, a fruſtrate
expectation is not.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that he ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt here is active,
whereas in his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and Satisfaction, he was paſſive.</hi> I
Anſwer, that herein he hath little obſerved the manner of the
expreſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, which ſpeaks of Chriſt even in his
ſufferings, under the notion of a Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and that even upon the Croſs,
when he was a paying the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, he was in the Conqueſt of his
enemies. <hi>He ſpoiled Principalities and Powers, and made a ſhew of them,
openly triumphing over them in it,</hi> Col. 2.15. The Sufferings of Chriſt,
do not hinder him from being actively Victorious; nay, they are his actual and
active Victory. And ſo he makes his members likewiſe, even in their
ſufferings, more than Conquerors, through him that loved them, <hi>Rom.</hi>
8.36,37. Even when they are killed all the day long. <hi>Suffering and
Conqueſt,</hi> Spiritual Conqueſt are not ſo inconſiſtent, as Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> would perſwade us.</p>
            <p>As for his ſcoff of <hi>Doctor infallibilis</hi> in the Margent,
he might have kept it at home till he had met with a man which arrogated any
ſuch thing to himſelf, or a people that aſcribed any ſuch thing unto
any. We ſay of him as <hi>Paraeus</hi> doth of <hi>Calvin</hi> (Par. in 2d.
cap. ad Gol. Lect. 22.) <hi>We pretend not his Name, we were not Baptized into
it, although his Doctrine we do deſervedly hold and defend as being agreeable
to the Holy Scriptures; yet not becauſe it is his, but becauſe it may be
evidently ſhewn to agree with the Truth of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>"<hi>Sect.</hi> 6. The <hi>Dr.</hi> ſaith, A Believers
Afflictions are not <hi>For,</hi> but <hi>From</hi> 
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98510:27"/> Sin.
<hi>This Diſtinction</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>Geree</hi>) <hi>is ſilly,
contradicts it ſelf, is pure non-ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſpeaks ſuch Language as he hath Learned, but
not in the School of Chriſt. Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> in a Sermon before the
Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, <hi>December</hi> 22. 1641. hath theſe Expreſſions:
<hi>It is not enough to be broken For ſin; we muſt alſo be broken From
ſin.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Let me moſt earneſtly Exhort you to
Repent From ſin, as well as For ſin.</hi> Now, if I ſhould take Mr.
<hi>Geree</hi>'s Expreſſions and Reaſons, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this diſtinction,
I ſhould call it <hi>ſilly, and contradictory to it ſelf, and
non-ſenſe;</hi> becauſe a Medicine is ſaid to be For, not From the
<hi>Plague,</hi> and it is to preſerve From it, in that it is For it, might
not any man juſtly, for ſaying it is Non-ſenſe, &amp;c. account me a
Ridiculous Reviler? Surely there are no Reaſons againſt Afflictions for and
from ſin; but they may with equal Weight (that is none at all) be applyed
againſt repentance for and from ſin. That the ſame diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will
not well ſuit with his ſimilitude of a Medicine for the Plague, is
becauſe ſuch medicine hath but a ſingle relation, <hi>i. e.</hi> only to
the Diſeaſe it is to Cure: But Afflictions may have a double One, to ſin,
conſidered <hi>as paſt,</hi> and unavoidable; in reference unto which, it
may be ſaid to be Affliction <hi>For</hi> ſin; another, to ſin,
conſidered as <hi>future,</hi> or rather not committed; in reference unto
which, it may, in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, be ſaid to be affliction <hi>From</hi>
ſin; that is, to preſerve from ſin: not as the <hi>effect per ſe,</hi>
of the afflictions, but as afflictions, do ſome way occaſionally ſtir up
Faith, which ſtirs up in the true Believer, a real wreſtling againſt all
ſin. And herein did the Dr. ſufficiently expreſs himſelf, what he meant
by <hi>For</hi> and <hi>From</hi> ſin, if Mr. <hi>G.</hi> had not been
willing to miſtake, that I may ſay no more.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea,</hi> (but ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) <hi>for ſin is
nothing elſe but from ſin.</hi> Herein your Medicine for the Plague
deceived you; otherwiſe you might have obſerved that <hi>for ſin,</hi>
notes ſin to be the <hi>impulſive cauſe</hi> of the Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; whereas
from ſin, notes ſin to be avoided, to be the <hi>final cauſe</hi> of the
Affliction. And theſe are not all one. The Learned <hi>Grotius</hi> (<hi>De
ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factione Chriſti cap.</hi> 1.) hath obſerved, That <hi>as often
as this phraſe</hi> [for ſins] <hi>is joyned to words of ſuffering, it
alwayes ſignifieth the impulſive cauſe.</hi> Which is moſt true, if
only the difference of the Type and the Anti-type be obſerved, and the
impulſive cauſe accordingly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. For if you grant
<hi>Socinus</hi> but that which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> here affirmeth, That
<hi>for</hi> ſin, is all one with <hi>from</hi> ſin, he will eaſily
fruſtrate the ſatisfaction and expiation of Chriſt. For if his dying for
ſin, note nothing elſe but the final cauſe, <hi>viz.</hi> That he might
thereby teach us to avoid ſin, then Chriſt, in regard of any Expiation of
Sin, hath utterly dyed in Vain.</p>
            <p>Now concerning puniſhments and chaſtiſements for ſin,
whether they be incident to Believers or not; Although Mr. <hi>G.</hi> by his
ſlight and <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98510:28"/> perfunctory paſſing it over, hath not
given occaſion of any full and large diſcourſe, but have taken up the
moſt trivial Arguments; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto (he cannot be ignorant), That
ſatisfactory Anſwers have been given, unto which he hath ſaid nothing at
all, for the ſatisfaction of the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: I ſhall ſay a few things
briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Theſe words of <hi>Puniſhing</hi> and
<hi>Chaſtizing for Sin,</hi> can denote no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the Meritorious
and Impulſive cauſe, namely, That ſin is the meriting cauſe, and
chaſtiſements and puniſhments are the merited effects. This
<hi>Grotius,</hi> whom I cited before, hath fully evinced againſt
<hi>Socinus,</hi> whoſe words are theſe: <hi>It cannot be ſhewn, that
theſe words</hi> [<hi>ob peccata,</hi> or <hi>propter peccata,</hi> that is,
for ſin] <hi>eſpecially where they are joyned to ſufferings, are ever
taken otherwiſe in the Holy Scripture, than in this ſignification of
merit.</hi> Where alſo he gives ſatisfaction to thoſe Scriptures which
were by <hi>Socinus</hi> cited to the contrary. Now if any part of the juſt
merit or deſert of the ſins of believers, be (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the
ſatisfactory ſufferings of Chriſt) laid upon believers to bear them in
their own perſons; then it is moſt evidently apparent, that Chriſt did
not, or did not ſufficiently bear the full merit and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of ſin. And
that theſe ſufferings being inflicted in a way and courſe of juſtice,
Chriſt hath not, by his death, fully ſatisfied the demands of Juſtice,
then which nothing can be ſaid more dangerous and deſtructive to the very
foundation of Chriſtian faith. Yet</p>
            <p n="2">2. I believe that ſin, as the impulſive cauſe and
puniſhment, or cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſement, as the effect of ſin, may be conſidered
two Wayes. 
<list>
                  <item>1. In a <hi>Typical</hi> conſideration.</item>
                  <item>2. In a <hi>Moral.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I do not ſay, that he did bear the whole <hi>Typical</hi> charge
of ſin (pardon the expreſſion, I cannot meet with one more fit at this
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) for that were to make him the <hi>Type</hi> of himſelf. That
charge of ſin was born wholly by the people of the old and typical Covenant,
both in their perſons and adminiſtrations, even until the very death of
Chriſt; wherein was exhibited the full Anti-type, who only bore the ſins of
his people, in the full merit and deſert of them <hi>Morally</hi> or
<hi>Really,</hi> as <hi>(Real)</hi> is oppoſed to the <hi>Type.</hi> For in
the Death of Chriſt the Old Covenant, with all its <hi>Types,</hi> had an
end; and the New Teſtament or Covenant, became in force, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.16,
17. <hi>A Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament is of force after men are dead, otherwiſe it is of no
force at all whilſt the Teſtator liveth.</hi> But the Old Covenant did
thereby <hi>decay, wax old, and vaniſh away,</hi> Heb. 8.13. Yet, as I ſaid
before ſeveral times (and ſay it again, that if it be poſſible, the
truth of what we hold might appear unto all men, breaking through thoſe many
clouds of ſlander wherewith we have been and are encompaſſed) I ſay,
that by the promiſe of the Meſſias, or by the promiſed Meſſias,
they were <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98510:28"/> all freely and perfectly before God juſtified,
they as we, and we as they, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.11. Chriſt bore the full
<hi>Moral</hi> or <hi>Real</hi> charge of their ſins, in the ſame meaſure
as he did ours. Only, I ſay, with all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Proteſtants, that the
<hi>Typical</hi> and <hi>Subſervient</hi> Adminiſtration or Covenant, did
exceedingly darken this upon their ſpirits; not to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the benefits of
Chriſt, that they ſhould not ſo ſpiritually come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them: But only,
that the enjoyment ſhould not be with that <hi>Luſtre and Glory</hi> as
they are ſet forth to be <hi>enjoyed in the New Teſtament;</hi> whereunto
therefore in ſome meaſure the Goſpel is reſtrained, and it is by way of
glorious eminence, ſtyled the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Even that
adminiſtration of the Goſpel of the grace of God here on earth,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 3.2. and 26.29. So then, we ſay, that as all <hi>Types</hi>
ceaſed at the death of Chriſt; ſo likewiſe did all Typical charging of
ſin therewith all ceaſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Albeit we acknowledg the ſame, or rather more hard
things to fleſh and blood, do uſually befall the children of the New
Teſtament, then did thoſe of the Old, in regard of the ſharpneſs
whereof, and the event alſo that they have in their converſation, they are
ſomtimes called chaſtiſements, or corrections, or Rebukes: Yet their
great conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation is, that it is not the good pleaſure of God, their well
pleaſed, and fully reconciled Father, that they ſhould in any way bear the
deſert and merit of there own ſin charged upon them, either
<hi>typically,</hi> as though the true Lamb of God which was to bear the ſins
of the world, and take them away, were not yet come; or <hi>Really,</hi> as
though there were no Lamb of God at all for them, that either had or ever would
ſuffer for their ſins. So that their preſent ſufferings be they never
ſo ſmart, yet are but trials and exerciſes of faith, and therein pure
teſtimonies of love, not of Anger or of Punitive Juſtice, to the
ſpiritual eye, which diſcerneth all things even as they are the
diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, not only of a Father, but alſo of a well-pleaſed
Father, in and through his beloved Son, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.17. For although here
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and to the eyes of fleſh, all things ſeem to be black, cloudy and
tempeſtuous; yet the eye of faith mounts up above the clouds, and there
diſcerns the full ſerenity of Heaven, notwithſtanding the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
appearances here below. And if in the wayes of God herein to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, there
ſeems to be ſome reference unto ſin, yet is it not to ſin in its own
nature, as it is the tranſgreſſion of Gods Law, calling for juſtice
from God in ſome way or other; for ſo it was utterly purged and done away
by the Death of Chriſt, <hi>Heb</hi> 1.3. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. But as they
are grievances unto Gods people, as they are a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al trouble and vexation
unto them in diſhonouring the Lord, before their own hearts or the eyes of
others; and ſo making the way of the Lord to be evil ſpoken of, then which
nothing goes more to the <pb n="48" facs="tcp:98510:29"/> quick, even to the heart of the
truly faithfull in moſt ſerious com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction. In this accidental
conſideration, I ſay affliction may have ſome relation unto ſin. 1.
Taking out of the way Earthly and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things; and thereby, 2. Making way
for faith to look upon the inviſible things of the Goſpel. By the activity
and power where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we are at leaſt in ſome meaſure freed from that thorn
in the fleſh which before did more infeſt us. So the Lord makes all things
work for the beſt, to them that are the called according to his purpoſe,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We ſay that in regard that Kingdomes, Congregations,
and Churches, are mixt aſſemblies at leaſt before God, conſiſting of
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that are in ſeveral ſtates and conditions Spiritually, though
things may generally be ſpoken in reference to ſuch collective bodies, yet
ought they to be particularly applyed and underſtood properly only to relate
unto ſuch a party, and ſuch perſons, in that collective body, in regard
of whom ſuch things are attributed unto ſuch a general body, ſo
<hi>Rom.</hi> 11.15,18. where the Jews are ſaid to be <hi>caſt away,</hi>
and broken off: <hi>Calvin</hi> obſerveth, and it is clear enough in the
Text, that it ought <hi>to be underſtood of ſuch as had not a real, but
only a ſeeming union unto the true Olive, according to that of our Saviour;
from him ſhall be taken away even that which he ſeemeth to have,</hi> Luke
8.18. [And <hi>Paraeus;</hi> but <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Ye are fallen from
Grace.</hi>] Anſwereth, 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>That the Apostle, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the
Scripture, attributes that to all which belonged but to a part; to the whole
body of the Church, which belonged but to a few members.</hi>"</q> So that
although puniſhments or chaſtiſements for ſin may be applyed to the
Churches of God in general, as to that of <hi>Corinth</hi> or <hi>Sardis,</hi>
&amp;c. it may not thence be inferred, that thoſe ſufferings for ſin had
a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular relation to the truly Faithful in thoſe Churches, but rather
the manner of the Scripture phraſe, as <hi>Paraeus</hi> ſaith, is to be
conſidered, which is to attribute to the whole that which may not be
attributed to every Member. And therefore the ſuffering of collective Bodies
and Churches is impertinent unto the preſent Queſtion.</p>
            <p>But the true ſtate of the Queſtion, is, <hi>Whether true
Believers in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, under the time and ſtate of the New Teſtament,
may be ſaid any way, either typically or really to bear the merit, or just
deſert of their ſin, either in whole or in part?</hi> This we utterly deny;
becauſe the Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is, 1. Againſt the Promiſe of God, <hi>Luk.</hi>
1.72,74. 2. Againſt the Oath of God, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54.9. 3. Againſt the
New and Everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God; <hi>Your ſins and iniquities will I
remember no more,</hi> Heb. 8.12. 4. Againſt the full ſatisfaction of
Chriſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14. 5. Againſt that perfect Reconciliation we have
with God our Father, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19. 6. Againſt our compleat
Juſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.8. 7. Againſt that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
Diſtinction of the Two Teſtaments in their Adminiſtrations, <hi>Gal.</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98510:29"/> 4.1,2,3,4,5. Now let us weigh Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s
Arguments to the contrary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He grants us, <hi>They are not properly
Puniſhments.</hi> Howbeit, we have it preached here by ſome of no ſmall
Note, That God puniſheth his own Children ſooneſt, ſoreſt, and
longeſt, through a wilful (ſhall I ſay) Neglect of the ſearching into
the difference of the Teſtaments, which <hi>Calvin</hi> well obſerved when
he makes it the Priviledge of the New Teſtament, that in it there is no more
remembrance of ſin, upon <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.18. whereas in the Old Teſtament
there was often a freſh remembrance of ſin, not in their ſacrifices
onely, but alſo in their ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, as appears largely in the Examples of
<hi>Moſes, David, Jehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> and others: But <hi>if ſtill</hi>
(ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 4. Sect. 30.) <hi>we are
puniſhed for our ſins, what I pray you had Chriſt performed for us?</hi>
Where alſo, he following the foot-ſteps of the Holy Ghoſt, makes
<hi>Puniſhments,</hi> and <hi>Chaſtiſements,</hi> and
<hi>Corrections</hi> (if they be for ſin) all one; neither is there any
ground in Scripture to diſtinguiſh them. <hi>This ſame,</hi>
(<hi>viz.</hi> that we are not puniſhed for ſin) ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi>
Eſay <hi>declareth, when he ſaith, That the Chaſtiſements or Correction
of our Peace was upon him. What is the Correction of our Peace, but the
Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to our ſins, which was to have been ſuffered by us,
before we could be reconciled to God, unleſs he had taken our Turns? Behold
thou ſeeſt plainly that Chriſt ſuffered the puniſhment of ſins,
that he might free his from them.</hi> But Mr. <hi>G.</hi> to prove, that the
Chaſtiſements of Gods Children are for ſin, urgeth <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.19.
<hi>As many as I love, I rebuke and chaſten:</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he finds not
<hi>[for ſin]</hi> here, he fetcheth it out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.11.
<hi>When thou with rebukes doſt chaſten man for ſin, thou makeſt his
beauty to conſume away.</hi> I Anſwer, Theſe places do not well ſuit
together: 1. The one ſpeaks of Gods beloved Ones, <hi>as many as I love;</hi>
the other mentions onely man, <hi>when thou with rebukes doſt chaſten
man:</hi> Which Expreſſion doth not neceſſarily include the
Faithful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The one belongs to the Old Adminiſtration,
the other to the New.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The one ſpeaks of Rebukes of Love, the other
of conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Rebukes, which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> in <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. of this
Sermon, grants not to be fatherly; theſe Texts therefore ought not to be ſo
jumbled together, as if they had both one Matter in hand.</p>
            <p>His ſecond Scripture is that of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
11.30,32. Where he ſaith, <hi>For this cauſe many are weak and ſickly
among you,</hi> &amp;c. Even among them that are judged of the Lord, that they
might not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the World. This place I confeſs is the onely one
in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in the whole Scripture: Yet is not the evidence of it ſuch,
that it can be able to ſhake the Faith of that which hath been before
eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon ſuch firm and fundamental Grounds of the full
ſatisfaction and propitiation by the blood of Chriſt, expreſſed in
ſuch legible and clear <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98510:30"/> Characters, in the free and new
Covenant of Grace, <hi>Your ſins and ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities will I remember no
more.</hi> For the right underſtanding therefore of this Text, I refer the
Reader to that which I have ſaid before, in the fourth Concluſion
concerning mixt aſſemblies, wherein, although things be ſpoken in general
of all, both good and bad, as they ſtand in relation to ſuch an
Aſſemble; yet as they are conſidered abſolutely in their own particular
Perſons, without the conſideration of ſuch a Relation, ſo ſuch an
Attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath no reference unto them. If an <hi>Engliſh-man</hi> ſhould
be put to death in a National Quarrel, it is therein the ſuffering of the
whole Nation, as injury and diſgrace of the whole Nation, yea, and every
particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Nation, as they are conſidered in that link and
Union Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, with all and every particular <hi>Engliſh-man:</hi> So in
the natural bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the ſuffering of a Toe, is by Natural Union the
ſuffering of a Head, although no part of the Head be touched. So might it be
ſaid of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that She, to wit, in ſome of her
Members, was <hi>judged of the Lord for ſin that She might not be condemned
with the World;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though neither the whole Church was ſo iudged in all
its particular Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers abſolutely conſidered, no nor in any one of thoſe
who were truely Members, by being united to the reſt by one ſpirit: And
alſo She, that is the Body of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> might be ſaid
to be chaſten'd of the Lord, in the removal of Corrupt Members from her, that
ſhe might not be condemned with the World, although thoſe Corrupt Members
in their abſolute conſideration in themſelves, were indeed condemned with
the World. The not obſerving the difference of Predications in this kind,
hath occaſioned a wonderful Confuſion in all points of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; whereas
the diligent obſerving of them would very much clear and explicate great
difficulties: So then, both according to the ſcope of the Text, and the
Analogy of Faith, it may be expounded thus: <hi>For this cauſe</hi> (that is,
for the Prophanation of the Lords Supper, by drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſuch like,
<hi>ver.</hi> 21.) <hi>many among you are weak and ſickly, and many
ſleep;</hi> (that is, many of thoſe Offenders, of which he ſpake of
before, which ye retained among you)
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>for if we did judge,</hi>
ſo the laſt Tranſlation, but it ought rather to be, if <hi>we did
diſcern;</hi> not <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if we did diſcern or ſift
our ſelves, (that is, ſeparate the Pretious from the Vile, put away from
our Communion ſuch Notorious Offenders) <hi>we</hi> (that is, the Church of
<hi>Corinth</hi> being a Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Body)
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhould not be judged,</hi>
(<hi>viz.</hi> in ſuch Corrupt Members, and in the whole, as relating to
ſuch Members) <hi>but being judged,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (that is, being puniſhed in
ſuch Members, and ſo in the whole Body, as having relation to them)
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>we</hi> (that is, the Church
of <hi>Corinth</hi> in our whole Body collectively ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) <hi>are
chaſtiſed</hi> (nurtured or inſtructed) <hi>of the Lord, that we ſhould
not be condemned with the World,</hi> (that we might not be accounted a
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98510:30"/> Society, ſuch as the World affords, and that we
might not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time become onely a Field, conſiſting onely of
Bryars and Thorns, by the admittance and continuance of evil doers, and the
departure of the faithful, we become a reprobate Society, which ſhall be
condemned with the World;) From hence, without queſtion, it cannot be proved,
that any particular. Elect Perſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bſolutely conſidered, ſuffers in any meaſure the juſt
deſert of his ſins, which Chriſt onely hath effectually, and perfectly,
and all-ſufficiently undergone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Mr. <hi>G</hi> urgeth, that <hi>Zachary was
ſtruck dumb becauſe of his unbelief,</hi> Luk. 1.20. I Anſwer, that this
is within the verge of the Old Teſtament, which ends not till the death of
Chriſt, where the New be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. which appears by our Saviours
ſubmitting to all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances thereof, even to the day of his death; for
he ate the Paſs-over immediately before: And by that Adminiſtration,
<hi>Zachary</hi> with the reſt of the Children of God belonging to that
Teſtament, was yet under the School-maſter, and ſo under the Whip; which
the Children of ripe Age are freed from, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.1,2,6,7.
<hi>chap.</hi> 3.25. When the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, <hi>Now</hi> (in the time of
the New Teſtament) <hi>ye are all the ſons of God,</hi> Gal. 3.26. <hi>He
underſtandeth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paraeus</hi> on the place) <hi>ſuch ſons
of God as are not little ones, under the ſchool-masters ferula, and the
cuſtody of Guardians, as the Fathers were, but ſuch as are of ripe age,
made free, and capable of their Fathers Inheritance.</hi> He ſaith therefore,
that the condition of the Fathers and ours, differs as much as an Heir that is
an Infant, differs from a Son that is of ripe Age. So <hi>Calvin, vid. ipſum
&amp; Mailor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> His laſt place is that of <hi>Peter,</hi> 1
Pet. 4.17,18. <hi>The time is come that judgment muſt begin at the houſe
of God,</hi> (as they are oppoſed to the wicked and ungodly) ſaith Mr.
<hi>Geree;</hi> for it follows, <hi>and if it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at us, what ſhall be the
end of thoſe that obey not the Goſpel of God? And if the Righteous are
ſcarcely ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner appear?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Anſwer, 1. That the Houſe of God, although it be by Vocation
and Profeſſion, a Company of Saints and Godly People, yet
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding there may be in it Wheat and Tares, good and bad; not
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret onely, but ſometimes open Offenders, through the fault or
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivance of thoſe whom it concerns; in reference unto which Offenders, the
Church may be ſaid to have Judgments come upon it: That God may firſt
cleanſe his own Houſe, by caſting out of it that which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth and is
unclean; ſo that there are ſome that are onely <hi>in,</hi> ſome that are
<hi>in</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the Houſe of God: Now Judgment may begin at the
Houſe of God, and yet, as a Judgment, it toucheth only the former. And
whereas it is ſaid, the <hi>Righteous are ſcarcely ſaved,</hi> it is not
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their ſalvation is in doubt or hazard; for this ſame Apoſtle
ſaith, <pb n="52" facs="tcp:98510:31"/> 
               <hi>they are kept by the mighty power of God
through faith unto ſalvation,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. But he ſpeaks in regard of
the rending of their Members, and the ſore trials which in their own
perſons they ſhould undergo, ſo that they ſhould in outward appearance
have thir faith ſifted to nothing, if it were not that the foundation of the
Lord ſtandeth ſure, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. That the Lord changeth not, and
therefore the ſons of <hi>Jacob,</hi> the faithful are not conſumed,
<hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> takes for granted, that
<hi>this judgment is for Sin,</hi> whereof he ought principally to have made
proof, is ſo far from being aſſerted in this Text, that the clear
contrary is evidently held forth. 1. In <hi>ver.</hi> 11. he calls this
affliction, <hi>a fiery tryal to try them:</hi> a metaphor taken from Gold,
which is not caſt into the fire to be puniſhed but purified; Yet this is
the darkeſt expreſſion. In the next, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. he calls it, <hi>a
partaking of Chriſts Sufferings,</hi> and bids them therein <hi>rejoyce.</hi>
Surely it were very unſeemly, and incongruous to ſee an offender rejoyce,
in ſuffering the juſt deſert of his offences. I am confident if we
ſhould make ſuch an exhortation, Mr. <hi>G.</hi> would ſay (as he doth
very falſly, and without ground in the end of this Section,) <hi>that we went
about to keep people from godly Sorrow.</hi> In the next words, <hi>ver.</hi>
14. he goeth higher, calling it <hi>Reproach</hi> not for Sin, but <hi>for the
name of Chriſt,</hi> and ſaith, that therein <hi>the Spirit of God, and of
Glory did reſt upon them.</hi> And in the laſt place both negatively, in
<hi>ver.</hi> 15. and affirmatively, in <hi>ver.</hi> 16. he calls it
<hi>ſuffering not as a murtherer, not as a thief, not, as an evil doer,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>but as a Chriſtian;</hi> wherefore he exhorts them not to be
<hi>aſhamed</hi> of it, but to <hi>glorify God</hi> in this reſpect, and
then ſubjoyns the words which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. And thus, if
the Chriſtian Reader will wiſely obſerve, the drift of the Holy Ghoſt,
he will not eaſily be carried away with ſuch impertinent, and perfunctory
allegations of Scripture. Alſo he may eaſily ſee that this is an
effectual, and truly Chriſtian humbling Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, (not a ſnarling
againſt Humiliation, as Mr. <hi>G.</hi> would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade,) To ſee the
overflowing bowels of the Lords tenderneſs to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us, that he will not any
more call our ſins to remembrance, or ſuffer the leaſt evil for them to
come nigh our dwellings. The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this unmeaſurable, and
undeſerved love, opens the heart ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually to a true ſerious and humble
acknowledgment with <hi>Jacob,</hi> that we are leſs than the leaſt of all
his mercies, and loving kindneſſes that have been ever of Old,
<hi>Gen.</hi> 30.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 7, 8, 9. Here the Dr. affirmeth, that altho' a
faithful man ſhould be overtaken with ſome groſs fault, yet ought he not
to add thereunto unbelief, by ſerving a writ of Damnation upon himſelf,
nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ought any other to do it: For, (ſaith he) thou that art ready 
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98510:31"/> to charge damnation upon thy ſelf, thou doeſt the
greateſt injury to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt that can be. For in it thou
directly overthroweſt the fulneſs of the grace of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> although he grant the matter, that <hi>none
ought to charge Damnation upon another:</hi> Yet, leſt he ſhould altogether
want matter of a Quarrel, he lays to him, 1. <hi>The unneceſſary uſe of
Logick,</hi> becauſe he proves what he ſaith, though for any <hi>Terms of
Logick,</hi> he here uſeth none. 2. Of <hi>Law-Terms,</hi> becauſe he
uſeth the Phraſe, of <hi>ſerving a Writ of Damnation.</hi> 3. Of
<hi>Exceeding Heat,</hi> becauſe he ſaith it is a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thing in any
man to ſerve ſuch a Writ. I entreat the Chriſtian Reader to pardon me, if
I paſs by ſuch trivial Cavils, which to recite, is to refute, which ſerve
to nothing but to blot Paper, to engender ſtrife, to hinder men from more
weighty and ſerious Matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. But, <hi>is the charging Damnation upon a mans
ſelf, the greateſt injury that can be done to Chriſt?</hi> I Anſwer,
that to ſtretch ſuch expreſſions as theſe upon the tentors, is a very
uncourteous thing. When a man dehorts another from any vice, what is more
uſual then to tell him that ſuch a vice, ſuch a courſe, is the moſt
dangerous way he can go in, that ſuch company is the moſt dangerous company
he can conſort with. Were it not a frivolous thing, to draw ſuch manner of
ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to the exact laws of compariſon. 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>What ſin</hi> (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>)
<hi>can be more execrable or horrible, than to reject the grace, and refuſe
that righteouſneſs that commeth by Chriſt: Which every one doth for the
time he doth not believe it.</hi>"</q> And a little after, <hi>This Blaſphemy
is more horrible than can be expreſſed: There is no ſin which</hi> Paul
<hi>and the other Apoſtles did ſo much deteſt, as the contempt of grace
and the denial of Chriſt, and yet there is no ſin more common.</hi> And a
little after, he tells us further, that <hi>all the world do ſo.</hi> And
upon the next, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. He adds, that <hi>as the whole world do this,
ſo eſpecially ſuch as will be counted more Holy and Religious than
others.</hi> Were it not a frivolous thing to alledg, that the falſe Teachers
amongſt the <hi>Galathians,</hi> might have been more execrable in their
Blaſphemy, if they had utterly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Chriſt; For now they went about to
joyn the Law together with him for juſtification?</p>
            <p>But this (ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) <hi>is the next way to make men
believe they have ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Is it ſo, to tell
them that they ought not to charge Damnation upon themſelves? To charge the
ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt upon themſelves, is inevitably to charge
Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation upon them, which he ſo earneſtly dehorts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yea, but the greateſt injury to the Lord Jeſus, is to
ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt: So that if they that have charged Damnation
upon themſelves, have done the greateſt injury to Chriſt, then have they
ſinned againſt the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> I Anſwer, that where Chriſt hath
diſtinguiſhed, we ought <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98510:32"/> not to confound. Chriſt hath
ſaid there is Sin and Blaſphemy againſt <hi>him,</hi> and there is Sin
and Blaſphemy againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> He ſaith, <hi>that all
Sin and Blaſphemy againſt him, ſhall be forgiven unto men; but the Sin
againſt the Holy Ghoſt ſhall never be forgiven.</hi> Now here Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> goes about to overthrow this diſtinction of Chriſt, telling us,
that the greateſt injury to Chriſt is the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt,
but he muſt pardon us, if we take Chriſts word before his, at leaſt till
he have proved it better, for here he offereth no proof at all, but his own
word directly againſt Chriſts, <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.31.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But ſurely,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thoſe that curſe and
ſwear by the name of the Lord Jeſus, by his blood and wounds,</hi> &amp;c.
<hi>And ſuch as deny Chriſt at</hi> Peter <hi>did, and perſecute him as
the Scribes and Phariſees did, do greater injury to Chriſt, than they that
charge Damnation upon themſelves for their paſt ſins.</hi> Oh Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> You look with the Phariſees, to much upon the outſide. Theſe
ſins are more outward and obvious, and are more ſenſible than the
ſecret unbelief of the heart; Is unbelief therefore leſs wicked? Is it not
the fountain from whence all theſe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes flow? Was it not want or
weakneſs of faith, that brought out all theſe you mention? You ſhould
rather have gathered from ſuch horrible effects, the greater horribleneſs
of the cauſe. You know the ordinary Axiome, <hi>Quod facit tale, eſt magis
tale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As unbelief bringeth forth all wickedneſs, ſo it is
the greateſt of all wickedneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Which is more pertinent to the preſent purpoſe:
Unbelief (as I have often heard Mr. <hi>Reinolds,</hi> whom you cite in your
Preface, ſay) <hi>is that which binds all the load of a mans other ſins
upon his back, and thereby it is the main condemning ſin.</hi> If a man have
received many deadly wounds, yet if there be one medicine that would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
heal them all, and but one, the rejection of this one medicine, muſt needs be
worſe, and more dangerous and deſtructive than all the wounds.</p>
            <p>And the Dr. ſaith, <hi>that ſuch unbelief, directly overthrows
the fulneſs of the grace and ſatisfaction of Chriſt.</hi> See here the
Courteſy of Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. Language: <hi>He will not ſay this is a
direct lye: But it is utterly falſe.</hi> Why? For, ſaith he, <hi>when they
thus charge damnation upon themſelves, they do not queſtion Chriſts
Satisfaction or Fulneſs of grace, but their own Faith and Condition, fearing
they are none of Chriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a good boulſter, and Apology for unbelief. It doth not
queſtion Gods Grace, but the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> is of another mind.
<hi>He that believeth not, hath made him a Lyar, becauſe he hath not believed
the Teſtimony that God gave of his Son. This is the Testimony, that God hath
given unto us Eternal life, and this Life is in his Son,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi>
5.10,11. Here by unbelief it is apparent, that not only the truth of God, 
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98510:32"/> but alſo the ſufficiency of that life laid up for us
in his Son, is queſtioned by him that chargeth Damnation upon himſelf.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi> they do only queſtion their own
faith. Surely he that queſtions his faith, ſo as to charge Damnation upon
himſelf, queſtions the Author and Finiſher of his Faith. For how is he
the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſher of it, if it fail even to Damnation? He Queſtions the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
of the Death and Satisfaction of Chriſt, whereby a faith that ſhall not
fail is purchaſed, <hi>Phil</hi> 1.29. He Queſtions the Power of God, which
is engaged to maintain our Faith even unto Salvation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>But that is unſufferable, which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath vented in
the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words; That <hi>they do more wrong to thoſe poor ſouls, in
ſaying ſo, than theſe do unto Christ.</hi> Is there any compariſon
between man and God? Is the greateſt injury that can be done unto man
(preciſely in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, which is the caſe in hand, ſeeing it
is oppoſed unto the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury done to Chriſt) comparable in heinouſneſs
to the leaſt injury a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt? Surely as the leaſt work of
Chriſt, by the dignity of the perſon, is of more Worth and Merit, than any,
than all the Works of the reſt of the ſons of <hi>Adam;</hi> yea, of
<hi>Adam</hi> himſelf in his Innocency, yea, of the Angels in Heaven: So
queſtionleſs the injury done againſt Chriſt, is by the ſame dignity
of his perſon of a deeper ſtain and demerit (as the School ſpeak) than
the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury that can be done to the beſt of the ſons of men,
which are but worms, <hi>Job</hi> 25.6. Yea, all Nations in compariſon of
him, are but as the neglected drop of a bucket, but as a ſmall duſt in a
ballance, that hath no weight to turn the ſcale hither or thither; yea,
leſs than nothing, <hi>Eſay</hi> 40.15,17. The Lord preſerve his People
from ſuch undervaluing words or thoughts of the Lord our
Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. The <hi>Doctor</hi> Objecteth, from the mouths
of ſome; That <hi>if there be no fear of Damnation, then men may do what they
liſt. No,</hi> (ſaith the Dr.) <hi>Chriſt is the guide of his people, he
takes as ſtrict order to reſtrain and keep in the Spirit of a man as to
Save him.</hi> Here obſerve, that that Slander which is frequent in Mr.
<hi>G.</hi> and others, namely, That a man Believing in Chriſt, may continue
ſtill in his Wickedneſs, was alwayes far from his mouth and thoughts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) <hi>may not a man
ſuſpect himſelf to be no True Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, when he cannot ſee that Christ
hath taken ſuch ſtrict order, as to reſtrain and keep his ſpirit from
ſuch ſins?</hi> I Anſwer no, he may not adde Unbelief unto his other
ſins. He ought to <hi>walk by Faith, though he cannot by Sight,</hi> 2 Cor.
5.7. He ought to remember, That <hi>this is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of
all acceptation,</hi> (and therefore of his preſent acceptation) <hi>that
Jeſus Christ came into the world to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. He
ought to imitate <hi>David, Wherefore ſhould I fear <pb n="56" facs="tcp:98510:33"/> in
the day of evil, when the iniquity of his heels compaſſeth him about,</hi>
Pſal. 49.5. He ought rather to give unto the Lord the glory of his Grace, the
glory of the Righteouſneſs, and Expiation of his SON. <hi>Thou needeſt
not fear</hi> (ſaith Dr. <hi>Preſton,</hi> of Gods alſufficiency,
<hi>pag.</hi> 91.) <hi>that thy diſobedience, if thou beest once within the
covenant, will cauſe the Lord to depart from thee</hi> (that ſo thou
ſhouldſt charge Damnation upon thy ſelf) <hi>for he will not be
unfaithful to thee, though thou be weak in thy carriage to him: For he keepeth
covenant for ever. He doth not ſuſpend his promiſe of help upon our
Diſobedience.</hi> That weighty ſaying of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> is very
conſiderable upon <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.2. <hi>When that great Dragon, that old
ſerpent the Devil, who deceived the whole world, and accuſeth our
bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and in the preſence of God day and night, cometh and layeth to thy
charge, that thou haſt not only done no good, but hast alſo
tranſgreſſed the Law of God; ſay unto him, Thou troubleſt me with the
remembrance of my ſins paſt, thou puttest me alſo in mind that I have
done no good; But this is nothing to me: For if either I truſted in mine own
good deeds, or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſted, becauſe I have done none, Christ ſhould
both wayes profit me nothing at all.</hi> See alſo what the Holy Martyr, Mr.
<hi>Bradford,</hi> anſwereth to this inference of Mr. <hi>G.</hi> (in a
Letter to Mrs. <hi>H.</hi>) <hi>If we want this obedience and worthineſs
which he requireth, ſhould we doubt whether he be our Father? Nay</hi>
(ſaith he) <hi>that were to make our obedience and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the cauſe,
and ſo to put Chriſt out of place, for whoſe God is our Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) <hi>I do not ſay, that
any ſin can cut off a true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever from Chriſt, or hinder his
Salvation.</hi> If this be true, then may he not ſuſpect the contrary,
which Mr. <hi>G.</hi> affirmed in the immediately foregoing words:
"<hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it must needs ſhake his hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,
and hinder his conſolation.</hi> What a thing doth <hi>de facto,</hi> and
what it ought to do <hi>de jure,</hi> and of right are not all one: And
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this is not to the purpoſe. We confeſs that all ſins, both
ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and actual, great and ſmall, have this as their natural and
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual effect, that they wound the Conſcience, that they enfeeble the
confidence, that they damp the conſolation of a Chriſtian, and ſo do as
it were becloud the Heavens between us and the appeaſed face of God our
Father; which cloud is no otherwiſe diſpelled, but by the appearance of the
Sun of Righteouſneſs, Faith aſcending up even through the blackeſt
cloud that is all darkneſs, and no light, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hold on the
Propitiation.</p>
            <p>But he tells us, <hi>We are not of</hi> Davids <hi>ſpirit, that
are ſo little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for groſs ſins, but can preſently cloſe with
Chriſt upon ſuch foul Falls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer</hi> 1. Here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> goes beyond his
knowledge: <hi>No man know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the things of man, but the ſpirit of man which
is in him,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11. <pb n="57" facs="tcp:98510:33"/> 
               <hi>But the heart knoweth its
own bitterneſs, and a ſtranger doth not intermeddle with his jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Prov. 14.10. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſe the Children of God having leſs light of the
Redeemer, were thereby more under the ſpirit of bondage unto fear, than the
Children of the New Teſtament are, who have received the ſpirit of
Adoption, to cry, Abba Father (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15.) we have the more cauſe to
praiſe the Lord, that hath reſerved better things for us (<hi>Heb.</hi>
11.40.) than he did for many Prophets and Kings who have <hi>deſired to ſee
the things which we ſee, and have not ſeen them;</hi> and to <hi>hear the
things which we hear, and have not heard them,</hi> Luke 10.24. to wit, <hi>the
full Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Myſtery of the Goſpel of Peace, which in other Ages
was not known, as it is now in the time of the New Teſtament reavealed,</hi>
Eph. 3.5. I ſay, if God hath been pleaſed to eſtabliſh our hearts, with
his free Spirit which <hi>David</hi> Prayed for, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.12. and
reſtore us ſomewhat ſooner than he did <hi>David,</hi> to the joy of his
Salvation, are we therefore not of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit? <hi>And</hi> ſo
as the Apoſtle ſaith, we having the ſame ſpirit of faith, according as
it is written (to wit of <hi>David</hi>) <hi>I believed and therefore have I
ſpoken;</hi> we alſo believe, that the Lord for his own SONS Sake alone,
hath done away our iniquities as a cloud, and our tranſgreſſions as a
miſt, and that he will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber our ſins no more, and therefore ſpeak, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13. But what is to be thought of Godly ſorrow for ſin, and
how we approve of it and practiſe it, if there be not inſtead thereof,
obtruded upon us an inforced howling for wine and oil, and ſelf-love
inconſiſtent with true faith, and the genuine effects thereof, I have
ſpoken of it before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 10. Hence the Dr. inferreth by way of anſwer to
an objection; That <hi>it is the power of Chriſt, and the Beauty of
Holineſs that draws out the ſpirits of Gods people to a willing ſervice
unto him, and not the fear of Damnation,</hi> Pſal. 110.3.</p>
            <p>Here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> Anſwereth, that therein the Dr. contradicts
what he ſaid before, <hi>Pag.</hi> 37. That <hi>God hampers Ephraim,</hi>
meaning by chaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements. Why ſo? Hath God no way of chaſtiſing, but
by threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Damnation? Hath a father no other way to nurture his ſon, but
by threatning to hang him up ſtrait, or to run him through? I Anſwer, that
here he ſpeaks of a people as converted and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving: But what he ſpake
of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> he ſpake of him in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his unconverted
eſtate, and ſo not ſpeaking of the ſame, M. <hi>G.</hi> may eaſily
perceive there can be no contradiction. That which he adds, <hi>that Chriſt
threatned the damnation of Hell to ſome Phariſees,</hi> Matt. 23.33. And
diverſe other times, to ſeveral Churches in the <hi>Revel. Chap.</hi> 2.
&amp; 3. is altogether as impertinent as the former; becauſe none of theſe
places ſpeak of particular believing Chriſtians, but either of notorious
hypocrites and unbelievers, or elſe of mixt congregations <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98510:34"/> conſiſting of chaff and wheat, which when he ſaith he will burn
up with unquenchable fire, he is to be underſtood of the chaff only: for he
hath promiſed to gather the wheat into his garner, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.12.
Neither doth the Scripture any where determine by way of Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or denounce
by way of threatning, that the truly faithful if they ſin ſo or ſo they
ſhall be damned; but the clean contrary, namely, that, <hi>he that believeth
in the Son of God hath Eternal life, and ſhall not enter into condemnation,
but is paſſed from death to life,</hi> Joh. 5.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 11. The Dr. here affirms, <hi>that the graſs and
paſture that Chriſt hath put a believer into, is ſo ſweet, that though
their be no bounds to keep in ſuch a Soul, yet it will never go out of this
fat paſture to feed in a barren common. "This he hath ſaid,</hi> ſaith
Mr. G. <hi>but not proved that the Paſture is ſo ſweet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely he might well have thought, that none profeſſing
himſelf a Chriſtian would have denyed it: For the common paſture of all
the faithfull, is that which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of Pſal. 23.2. <hi>He
maketh me to lye down in green paſtures, he leadeth me beſide the ſtill
waters, or the waters of comfort.</hi> This is the table which the Lord
prepareth for his people, at which he <hi>maketh their cup to run over,
ver.</hi> 5. How can they then but conclude with <hi>David</hi> in
<hi>ver.</hi> 6. ſurely <hi>goodneſs and mercy ſhall fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me all the
dayes of my life:</hi> And <hi>therefore I will dwell in the Houſe of the
Lord for ever.</hi> I ſhall have no deſire or delight, to follow after
lying vanities, for they are vain. He cannot but rejoyce that his lot is fallen
in ſo good a ground, that he hath ſo goodly an heritage; for the Lord is
the portion of his inheritance, therefore doth he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with <hi>Peter,
here are the words of Eternal Life, and whether ſhall we go,</hi> Joh. 6.68.
The grace and favor of God through Chriſt enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by faith, is that fountain
of living water which is in the bellies of the faithful, continually bubling
forth unto Eternal life, whereby they never thirſt again, to wit, after
thoſe loathſome and ſtoln waters, which although they may ſeem ſweet
to them that have taſted no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, who therefore long after them, yet to
the faithful that have taſted that the Lord is gracious, who have found that
the loving kindneſs of the Lord is better than Corn, than Wine and Oyl, than
any of the pleaſures of Sin, or promiſes of the World, yea, than life it
ſelf: They cannot forſake thoſe fountains of living water, to hunt after
broken ciſterns, which they know will hold no water.</p>
            <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>G. His Chriſt differs from the true
Chriſt.</hi> Oh! Mr. <hi>G.</hi> take heed what you do. Our Chriſt is no
other but the only begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Son of God, The King of Kings, and the Lord of
Lords: The Chriſt of the Patriarchs, of the Prophets, of the Apoſtles, of
all the Saints of God in all Ages. We have no peculiar Chriſt, but him that
came into the world to ſave ſinners. Take heed of ſtumbling at that
ſtumbling <pb n="59" facs="tcp:98510:34"/> ſtone, which on whomſoever it falls, it
grinds them to powder. And I beſeech every one who hath the leaſt dram of
reverence unto the Lord Jeſus C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſt, to conſider ſeriouſly, whether here was any the
leaſt occaſion given to ſpeak thus reproachfully of the Lords Chriſt,
or of imagining any other Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the true Chriſt,</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>G. told his
Diſciples that dreamed of ſuch dainties, that they muſt drink of a bitter
cup of Affliction.</hi> What then? Shall Chriſt therefore not be ſweet unto
them? Doth not he himſelf ſay, that in <hi>him they ſhould have peace,
though in the world they ſhould have tribulation?</hi> Is not he an hundred
fold recompence unto them even in this life for all their loſſes,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 19.29. whereby the bitter cup of affliction is ſo ſweetned
unto the truly faithful, that they even rejoyce in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, <hi>Rom.</hi>
5.2.</p>
            <p>Some of the Diſciples indeed dreamed of carnal dainties, and a
temporal Kingdom, to ſit upon Thrones. And let them be told of ſuch dreams
of dainties that look for Quiet, and Wealth, and freedom from the Croſs, that
hope, by the aſſiſtance of the Sword of the Magiſtrate, to cruſh all,
not only that oppoſe them, but that do ſo much as diſſent from them
even in the ſmalleſt matter; let thoſe, if there be any ſuch be told of
their carnal dreams: As for us, we have no ſuch thought of freedom from the
Croſs, ſo long as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> is alive, and abides in the houſe,
that is, until the Lord of the houſe ſhall come, who ſhall utterly caſt
out the bond-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and her ſon, who ſhall gather out of his Kingdom every
thing that offendeth. And notwithſtanding, we know, that although the Croſs
be not joyous, but grievous to the fleſh; yet is the ſpiritual bitterneſs
of it taken away ever ſince the Lord Jeſus made it a trophy of victory. So
that we dare boldly ſay with <hi>Calvin,</hi> (Inſtit. lib. 3. cap. 2.
ſect. 28.) <hi>That whatſoever miſeries and calamities befal thoſe who
are beloved of the Lord, they cannot hinder that his loving kindneſs ſhould
not be co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>leat fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity.</hi> And
a little after, <hi>If all things abound unto us, according unto our deſire,
and we be uncertain of the love or hatred of God, our felicity will be
accurſed, and therefore miſerable; But if the fatherly face of God ſhine
upon us, our very miſeries will be bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>G.</hi>) <hi>that which keeps us
from breaking our bounds, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bitterneſs than ſweetneſs, as the
Scripture,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>teſtifieth,</hi> but alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth none, only he
brings two Scriptures, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.9. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.23. to
prove that which none denies, that the remaining of the ſeed of God within
us, which is immortal, keeps us within bounds. Yea, we deny not, but that
Afflictions are very uſeful, as I ſaid, to Gods Children: Yet ſo, that
they alſo do ſome way ſweeten, rather than imbitter the paſtures where
the Saints do feed; though not to the fleſh and outward man, yet to the
ſpirit and inward man. For it is grace revealed, that teacheth effectually to
deny all <hi>ungodlineſs and worldly lusts,</hi> Tit. 2.11.12. Pſal. 26.3.
<hi>Thy <pb n="60" facs="tcp:98510:35"/> loving kindneſs is ever before mine eyes, and
therefore I have walked in thy truth.</hi> Chriſt is able to rule his own
Wife by the ſcepter of his Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 12. In the three laſt Sections, the Dr.
attributes unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt; 1. <hi>The
giving of Spiritual Sight,</hi> to ſee in a gracious manner, both our own
filthineſs and vileneſs, where a cloſing with Chriſt begins: This,
ſaith he, we have not from the Law, which though it be a perfect
looking-glaſs, yet it gives no eyes. 2. <hi>Repentance.</hi> 3.
<hi>Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> after his manner, hath found a
contradiction: Why? <hi>Becauſe hereafter he affirms Juſtification to be
before all qualification; But here, he ſaith, there is firſt the opening of
the eyes, and from the opening of the eyes, proceeds a cloſing with Chriſt.
Whereupon</hi> ſaith Mr. <hi>G. follows Juſtification.</hi> So that this
Juſtification after cloſing, is Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. Inference, not the Dr's.
Aſſertion. But I Anſwer, and Grant, that our Juſtification is
conſidered two wayes: 1. <hi>In the Court of Heaven;</hi> ſo it is
antecedent to any qualification. So ſaith Dr. <hi>Twiſs, The
Righteouſneſs of Christ, as it is Chriſts, in that it is performed by
Him; ſo it is ours, in that it was performed for us, and that before Faith,
as meriting for us effectual Faith. For the Righteouſneſs of Chriſt is
ſaid to be imputed to us, and his Merits to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to us by Faith, not
before God, but in our own Conſciences.</hi> But of this, as Mr. <hi>G.</hi>
ſaith, more hereafter. Onely this we muſt alwayes carry along with us, that
without Chriſt, that is, without being implanted into Him, as the Branches
into the Vine; and ſo without being united to Him, and juſtified by Him,
<hi>We can do nothing,</hi> Joh. 15.5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Here at length Mr. <hi>G.</hi> hath found ſomthing,
that he can, as he thinks, with ſome confidence call Antinomianiſme, that
the title of his book may not ſeem to be a meer ſlander. <hi>Here,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>the Dr. bewraies his malice againſt the Law of God.</hi> And
this he repeats again. What is the ground of this heavy charge? Surely only
this, that he ſaith that a gracious ſight of our own vileneſs, is the
work of Chriſt alone, and that the Law gives no eyes to ſee. Surely if this
be ſuch deep Antinomianiſm, there are more Antinomians than many are aware
of. For, <hi>Firſt,</hi> He grants the Law to be a perfect Look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Glaſs,
to repreſent the filthineſs of a perſon. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He doth not
deny, but by the Law a man may have a deep ſight of his own vileneſs, as
<hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He only affirmeth, that
al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Law compared with the heart and converſation of men, afford the
object, to wit, the filthineſs, that is to be ſeen; yet it gives neither
eyes to ſee, nor a gracious manner of ſeeing. Theſe two are only from
Chriſt, from his Grace, not from the Law. Both in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and grace, there is
the ſame fountain of Life, and of the effects of Life, as eyes and ſight.
That only which gives life, gives ſight. Now the Apoſtle utterly denies the
former, that the Law can give life, and thereby he denies it able to give
ſight. But contrarywiſe, as <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98510:35"/> Chriſt only gives life,
ſo He only gives ſight, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.17,18. And that not by the
Law, but by meer Grace. But how doth Chriſt give a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſpiritual
ſight or eyes? I Anſwer, by the Unction of his Spirit, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi>
2.20. who is therefore called the <hi>ſpirit of Wiſdom and
Illumination,</hi> Epheſ. 1.17. And <hi>the things of God knoweth no man, but
the Spirit of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 2.11. But doth Chriſt give theſe ſpiritual
eyes without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward means. I Anſwer, that I conceive that ſpiritual
eyes, with other gifts of grace may be conſidered two wayes; In their Root,
and in their Fruit: In their Being, and in their Actuating. In the former
ſenſe they are the immediate effects of the ſpirit, <hi>per modum
cauſae Phyſicae;</hi> But in the actuating or putting forth of Faith or
Sight, there is the intervening of the word, <hi>per modum cauſae moralis
ſive objecti,</hi> as the object to be ſeen, which is therefore ſaid to
enlighten the eyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.8. And ſo Faith is ſaid to come by
Hearing. Here the Word and the Spirit are alwayes conjoyned, <hi>Eſay</hi>
59.21. Well then, ſeeing without Chriſt and his Spirit, there is no
enlightning, either by the word of the Law, or the Goſpel; <hi>Why may he not
enlighten as well by the Law, as by the Goſpel?</hi> This is Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s
Objection. I Anſwer with the Apoſtle, The Goſpel only is the
miniſtration of the Spirit, and not the Law, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8. But the Law contrariwiſe, is the <hi>Law of Sin and
Death,</hi> Rom. 8.2. It is the <hi>Killing Letter,</hi> 2 Cor. 3.6. It is the
<hi>Miniſtration of Death,</hi> ver. 7. It is the <hi>Miniſtration of
Condemnation,</hi> ver. 9. <hi>We muſt obſerve,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paraeus,
That the Law is not the Miniſtry of the Spirit, that is, by the Preaching of
the Law the Holy Ghoſt is not given; and therefore neither Faith, nor
Confidence, nor any hope of Adoption or Salvation,</hi> Par. in Gal. 3.2. I may
add, (nor any other thing which is a proper effect of the Spirit, ſuch as is
a gracious ſight of our own vileneſs) <hi>The Law Commands only, but it
Helps not:</hi> But if it did give Eyes, or Sight, it ſhould Help as well as
Command. Neither is this any reproach unto the Law of God, which is <hi>Holy,
Juſt, and Good.</hi> It is Our fault, not the Laws, that it is not able to
give us Life, nor the effects of it. It is weak, not through any impotency in
its ſelf, but through our fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.3.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"But Mr. <hi>G.</hi> cites againſt us, out of
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.7,8. <hi>That the law converts the ſoul, makes wiſe
the ſimple, enlightens the eyes.</hi>"</q> But here he hath deceived
himſelf with the ambiguity of the word <hi>Law,</hi> which any ſmatterer in
Divinity knows ſometimes to be taken; 1. Generally for the whole word of God,
as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.2. And moſt frequently all the Pſalms through. 2.
Particularly and properly, for the Decalogue or covenant of works, given from
the beginning, but renewed upon Mount-Sinai, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3,4,5. 3. For the
Goſpel, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.3. where it is ſaid, the Law ſhall go out of
Sion. So then, as the Law in its primacy, and proper ſignification, doth
ſignifie a doctrine; and ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darily, <pb n="62" facs="tcp:98510:36"/> but moſt
uſually, the doctrine of God; ſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies
the whole word of God, which is in reference to that part of it only which
holds forth Chriſt, and Salvation, gives life and light, and wiſdom; that
is, the Goſpel, which is the power of God unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the believer,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. So ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place. <hi>David here
commends the whole doctrine of the Law, as comprehending the Goſpel, and
therefore including Chriſt in it. So</hi> ſaith Mr. G. <hi>the miniſters
are ſaid to open mens eyes by Preaching the word,</hi> Act. 26.18. True, but
it is the word of the Goſpel which is the miniſtration of the ſpirit,
<hi>Gal.</hi> 3.2. Which is the joyful news of the grace of God, <hi>Act.</hi>
20.24. Whereby alone we <hi>are partakers of the promiſe,</hi> Eph. 3.6. In
which ſpiritual eyes are contained, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.6. <hi>Faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
by hearing,</hi> Rom. 10.14. By hearing of what, or of whom? The next
<hi>ver.</hi> will ſhew you. <hi>As it</hi> is written, <hi>how beautiful
upon the mountains, are the feet of them that bring glad tidings of peace. For
the Law is not of faith,</hi> Gal. 3.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. The Dr. ſaith, that the giving of Repentance,
is meerly the work of Chriſt; here Mr. <hi>G.</hi> begins: what ſhall I
call it, but to boaſt himſelf? If I miſcall it, let the Reader judg.
"<hi>We teach Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance more and better than they.</hi> Hereunto I ſhall
ſay nothing, but deſire the Lord to open the mouths of all the Miniſters
of Chriſt, that they may more abundantly preach true chriſtian Repentance,
to a full and ſerious ſelf-denial in all things: That man may be taught to
own the ſhame of his own doings, that God may have the full glory of his free
grace in Chriſt.</p>
            <p> 
               <q rend="inline">"But Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſuſpects this word
<hi>(meerly)</hi> when it is ſaid, that it is <hi>meerly the work of Chriſt
to give Repentance.</hi>"</q>
            </p>
            <p>Here I confeſs, he hath picht upon the very point of all our
dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences. All our controverſies, in a manner, ly in this word
<hi>(meerly)</hi> or <hi>(onely)</hi> That Chriſt onely and meerly Saves;
that he onely and meerly gives Repentance and Faith. If we could but diſpence
to leave out this word, the world would be at peace with us. That it might be
lawfull for them to ſay, Chriſt and we Save: Chriſt and we give
Repentance and Faith: Chriſt and we pacifie Gods Anger. But utterly to
thruſt out man, that he may have no finger in theſe matters, makes him
ſtorm and fume, and deviſe all manner of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches againſt us. This
word, <hi>onely Faith,</hi> i. e. <hi>onely Chriſt,</hi> was the Apple of
contention, among the firſt reforming publiſhers of the Goſpel. 
<q rend="inline">"<hi>What</hi> (ſaid one of the Worthies of
former times) <hi>[Fulk de Chriſto gratis justificante] do we ſeek after in
Preaching, in Writing, in Labouring; what do we elſe, but that Christ</hi>
(only and meerly) <hi>may be received <pb n="63" facs="tcp:98510:36"/> by all, as the
Saviour and Redeemer of all? Contrariwiſe your Popiſh opinions, what do
they breath, what do they beat upon, whither do they tend, but to this one
thing, that Chriſt onely may not Reign alone in his Church? That he onely may
not Save and Redeem us by his ſelf alone; That he only and meerly may not be
our high Prieſt, who both made Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction for our ſins, with one onely
Sacrifice once made,</hi> &amp;c."</q> Though God hath eſtabliſhed a
miniſtry to preach Repentance, yet hath he eſtabliſhed none to give
Repentance: That is the peculiar prerogative of Chriſt. After the Miniſter
hath done his office by inſtructing in meekneſs, thoſe that are
contrary-minded, it remains ſtill to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, if God will give them
Repentance to the acknowledgment of the Truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sect.</hi> 14. Of Faith I have ſpoken before, in
<hi>Sect.</hi> 12. how it comes by hearing. Mr. <hi>G.</hi> demands further,
<hi>How he will make this good, that Faith is the root of all gifts of grace,
ſeeing he ſaith Knowledg is wrought firſt. Why did he put Repentance
before Faith, unleſs it went before it? Or elſe, doth he make Repentance
and Faith the ſame?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt Queſtion I Anſwer, that the knowledg the Dr.
ſpeaks of, is nothing elſe but the beginnings of Faith: Neither doth the
Scripture make ſuch an accurate diſtinction between them, <hi>Joh.</hi>
3.15. It is ſaid, that <hi>he that believeth on Chriſt, hath Eternal
Life,</hi> Joh. 17.3. It is ſaid, that <hi>to know him is Life Eternal;</hi>
where <hi>Believing</hi> and <hi>Knowing</hi> are words of the ſame
ſignification. <hi>By his knowledg, ſhall my Righteous Servant juſtifie
many,</hi> Iſa. 53.11. That is by Faith, in him. Alſo, where Faith is
called <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> Heb. 11.1. This Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
muſt needs include a knowledg. So then, knowledg, as the beginning of Faith,
may be ſaid to be wrought firſt, and yet no gift precede Faith.</p>
            <p>To the ſecond, <hi>why Repentance is mentioned before
Faith?</hi> I Anſwer as before; that although Repentance go not before Faith,
yet hath it reference to that ſtate which goes before Faith. But that in
nature nor time, it doth not go before Faith, I have partly manifeſted
before. And ſurely whatſoever is not Faith, is Sin.</p>
            <p>To his third Queſtion, <hi>whether we make Faith and Repentance
all one?</hi> I Anſwer, no, not adaequately. Yet we ſay there is no
Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance truely acceptable unto God, in whoſe difinition Faith is not. And
if Mr. <hi>G</hi>'s. obſervation be true, we may call Repentance Faith, and
Faith Repentance, and that by the Authority of the Scriptures (<hi>Pag.</hi>
73. in marg.). Surely this is putting a leſs difference between them.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:98510:37"/>4. He finds much fault with the Dr.
(although for ought I ſee, he is guilty of the ſame himſelf) that <hi>he
hath not defined Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi> And this he tells us
(<hi>Cato</hi>-like) <hi>he muſt needs note as a groſs overſight, if not
a wilful neglect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I Anſwer, 1. That the ſame definition of theſe that
he ſhall find in the Scripture, I will find in theſe Sermons. And therefore
Mr. <hi>G.</hi> ſhould not have paſſed his Cenſure, till he had made a
better ſearch. 2. If he had made an exact and logical definition, it may be
Mr. <hi>G.</hi> would not have been ſatisfied.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books Sold by <hi>Will. Marſhall</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi>
in <hi>Newgate-ſtreet.</hi> Books Lately Printed of Dr.
<hi>Owen</hi>'s.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>THE True Nature of a Goſpel Church, and its
Government,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in theſe following particulars are Diſtinctly
handled: 
<list>
                     <item>I. The Subject Matter of the Church.</item>
                     <item>II. Formal Cauſe of a particular Church.</item>
                     <item>III. Of the Polity, Rule, or Diſcipline of the Church
in General.</item>
                     <item>IV. The Officers of the Church.</item>
                     <item>V. The Duty of Paſtors of Churches.</item>
                     <item>VI. The Office of Teachers in the Church.</item>
                     <item>VII. Of the Rule of the Church, or of Ruling
Elders.</item>
                     <item>VIII. The Nature of the Polity or Rule, with the Duty of
Elders.</item>
                     <item>IX. Of Deacons.</item>
                     <item>X. Excommunication.</item>
                     <item>XI. Of the Communion of Churches. In large
<hi>Quarto,</hi> Price Bound 3<hi>s.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item> 2. A Treatiſe of the Dominion of <hi>Sin</hi> and
<hi>Grace.</hi> Price Bound 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 3. A Brief and Impartial Account of the Nature of the
<hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> its State and Fate in the World, its Strength
and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; with the Wayes and Indications of the Ruin or Continuance of
its Publick National Profeſſion. Price 6<hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 4. A Brief Inſtruction in the Worſhip of God, and
Diſcipline of the Churches of the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> by way of
<hi>Queſtions</hi> and <hi>Anſwers,</hi> with an Explication and
Confirmation of thoſe Anſwers. Price Bound 1<hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Where you may be Likewiſe ſupplied with the Reſt of Dr.
<hi>Owen</hi>'s Books that are in Print.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
